<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aulus Persius Flaccus his Satires translated into English, by Barten Holyday Mr of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
            <title>Works. English</title>
            <author>Persius.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19778.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855394</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 662:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aulus Persius Flaccus his Satires translated into English, by Barten Holyday Mr of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                  <title>Works. English</title>
                  <author>Persius.</author>
                  <author>Holyday, Barten, 1593-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, printer to the Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with Oxford device (McKerrow 336) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19778 on UMI microfilm reel 1607.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴ (-E4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin poetry --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Satire, Latin --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AVLVS PERSIVS FLACCVS HIS SATIRES TRANSLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED INTO ENGLISH, BY BARTEN HOLYDAY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, and Student of Chriſt-Church in Oxford.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hinc trahe que dicas, menſam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> relinque <hi>Mycenis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cum capite &amp; pedibus —</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond Impreſſion.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed By Ioſeph Barnes, Printer to the Vniverſitie, 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdicious Reader (for to Thee as to a Iuſt Patrone, I make my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication) with the true ſtingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I ſubmit theſe my endeavours, the not vnprofitable recreations only of ſeverer ſtudies. To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite thy attention, I may without ambition ſay it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a New thing, <hi>Perſius</hi> Vnderſtood. When firſt entertained the attempt, I was oppoſed by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing-inſuperable difficulties: The labouring to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pprehend, to Expreſſe the ſenſe of my Author: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he reconciling of contrarie expoſition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng out the order of his paſſages, grounded on a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aturall, but much concealed dependancy of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecedent and ſubſequent matter: the endeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to render him with brevity, perſpicuity and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Owne Strength: Laſtly the amputation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neceſſarie Criticiſmes of ſome Interpreters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om whom on juſt reaſon I ſometimes depart.</p>
            <p>And that in this point I may ſtand cleare from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e private ſurmiſe of ſome tacite cenſurer: I will
<pb facs="tcp:20884:3"/>
ſhew vnto thee, among many, two only of their curioſities, and thoſe in the front of the worke.</p>
            <p>The firſt is about the word <hi>Prolui,</hi> which ſome would haue to be heere vſed, to ſignifie that the Poet had modeſtly wet his lippes in <hi>Hippocrene,</hi> but never endrench'd them, or dranke deep ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I graunt that the word in the originall Can beare that ſenſe; but that it doth in This place, I confidently denie. And ſtand confirmed by this reaſon: becauſe the Poet ſatirically Derideth thoſe, that attributed the faculty of poetric to ſo inſufficient and vaine a cauſe, as the drinking of that Well was. (He himſelfe afterwards confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ironically, his Owne skill to be Conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: howſoever, not proceeding from ſo Fond a cauſe;) and therefore in the like ſort preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he ſaith (if the Critiques had obſerved it) tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he never ſlept on <hi>Parnaſſus:</hi> which was alſo held as another cauſe of the poetique faculty. Where with reaſon, as good as theirs, one might ſay, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never ſlept Soundly or Snorted on that hill, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had lightly taken a gentle nap. The parts of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſimilitude hold an equall proportion: and then referre the ridiculous curioſity to the ſecret ſmile of the Iudicious.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is about the next word <hi>Caballino</hi> with which, according to Their expoſition, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:5"/>
epithet which in my tranſlation I giue to <hi>Pega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> may ſeeme ſomewhat to ſtraine curteſie: inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it implyeth the ſwiftneſſe (and ſo by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent the praiſe) of the horſe, to which it is (iuſtly) applyed: when as They would haue it to be vſed in the diſgrace of the vaine Poets, which are heere derided. Deriving ſo the ignominie of the word <hi>Caballus</hi> from the Well to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: implying Them to be baſe packe-horſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets. A pretty, but impoſed meaning, if farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into. For if the poet vſe this word eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for that reaſon, it might ſeeme (me thinkes) that he did forget what horſe he himſelfe meant: there being as great difference betweene <hi>Pegaſus</hi> a winged horſe, and <hi>Caballus</hi> a packe-horſe, as well-nigh could bee betweene two creatures of one kind. But if they once come to Coniectures, I may aſſume the like libertie to interpoſe Mine alſo; And then I Could thinke (which, I wonder, the Critiques did not ſee) that the Poet vſed this word before others, for a moſt naturall &amp; ſtrong reaſon drawne from the <hi>Etymologie</hi> of the word <hi>Caballus;</hi> which, as <hi>Iſidore</hi> in his <hi>Originals</hi> hath it, <hi>Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. is deriued, <hi>à cavando: propter quòd gradiens vngulâ impreſſâ terram concavet, quod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liqua animalia non habent;</hi> And then who ſeeth not how excellently the hiſtory of <hi>Pegaſus</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated
<pb facs="tcp:20884:6"/>
in this word? This <hi>Etymologie</hi> is much ſtrengthened by the letter v changed into b. For in the Moderne languages which haue drawne their originall from the <hi>Latine,</hi> we ſee the v ſtill retained, as in the Italian and Spaniſh <hi>Cavallo,</hi> and in the French <hi>Cheval;</hi> and which may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, Theſe words in none of theſe Moderne languages imply any diſgrace, but are generally attributed to all horſes; Nay, from theſe words are drawne Titles of dignity, as <hi>Cavaliero,</hi> in the Italian, <hi>Chevalier</hi> in the French, and <hi>Cavallero</hi> in the Spaniſh.</p>
            <p>But (that I may follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no farther in theſe their wandring ſpeculations) to ſpeake freely: I thinke the Poet neither thought as They thinke, nor as I ſhew how I Could thinke, and thinke as well as They. I am perſwaded that more is pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of theſe Poets, then they themſelues ever meant. For indeed when a Satiriſt, through the heat of his loue to vertue, is ſet on fire to ſee the deſperate ſecuritie of prophaneſſe: the fury of his paſſion doth ſo tranſport him: that there is no time left for the placing or diſplacing, chooſing or reiecting of ſome particular word: but as moſt commonly their paſſions are vneven, rough, and furious: ſo is that alſo which they write being in this poeticall perturbation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:6"/>The difficulties which I haue heere ſet downe, were by my peculiar affection to This Author, at laſt all ouercome. I haue not herein bound my ſelfe with a ferulary ſuperſtition to the letter: but with the ancient libertie of a Tranſlator, haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a moderate paraphraſe, where the obſcuritie did more require it: yet ſo, that with all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient poſſibilitie, I ſticke vnto his Words. To haue added Large annotations, had beene but to tranſcribe a Commentarie or a Dictionary. Such briefe ones notwithſtanding, as without which, the ſenſe could not be ſufficiently explicate, yet could not bee well inſerted into the text; with all compendious perſpicuitie I haue adiected in the margin: prefixing Arguments to euery Satire.</p>
            <p>From the affected obſcuritie, wherewith this Author hath hitherto laboured, I cannot altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quitte him, yet doubtleſſe, it in part, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the want of Libertie, which in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate times, was altogether loſt; though, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, He durſt ſay Somewhat.</p>
            <p>As for My labours: I much abhorre ſo ſickly an impotencie, as to ouerweane my ſelfe with a conceit of mine owne worke; though, if my beſt friends tell me truth, It may beare a Iudge. But howſoeuer; If the truly Iudicious (who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb facs="tcp:20884:7"/>
attended with Perſpicacitie, &amp; a milde ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that true exciter of promiſing ingenuities) ſhall courteouſly accept it: I am Crown'd: and hauing thus finiſhed this worke of an Others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, I may be excited to a ſecond and more liberall attempt of mine owne.</p>
            <p>But if any Left-handed <hi>Pythagorians</hi> (who enforce Writers now adaies as the Ancients did their Comoedians, to vſe inſteed of Prologues expreſſing their arguments, Apologies againſt the malicious) ſhal ſiniſterly accept, what is cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly offered: I only wiſh them the other good qualitie of the <hi>Pythagorians, Sile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> For the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſights which I may bee perchance convinced of (as the pureſt eie ſeeth not its owne blemiſhes, but by reflection) I wil, being ſhewed them, with free ingenuity confeſſe: &amp; doubt not of pardon; hauing two ſo good ſolliciters in the eie of any, but moderately courteous; Mine Owne Infancy (in reſpect of any Maturity of iudgement) &amp; the vnacquainted Difficulty of my attempt. To haue committed No faults in my Tranſlation, had bin to Tranſlate My Selfe, and put off Man.</p>
            <p>What other faults Detracters woulde Make (by their Owne Reading, or Interpretation) let them knowe, they are committed not out of Ignorance, but Election, after a iuſt conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:20884:7"/>
with more then a <note n="*">Cornutus. Author vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Gloſſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Murmellius. Vinetus. Pithoeus. Marcilius. Foquelinus. Tornorupaeus. Lubinus. Caſaubonus. Friſchlinus. Bondus. Farnabius.</note> Dozen Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiters. But why doe I in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion of Too-much humilitie proſtrate my endeavors to the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the Ignorant: who ſtand Herein ſo Many degrees below the faculty of Iudging ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſurers? If any in the procacity of baſer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice (raiſed commonly from a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of Imitation) ſhall proceede farther vnto contumelies: I ſhall not need, as ſome doe (though I approue Their courſe alſo) to arme my ſelfe with a confidence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; I will not put it to the ſtreſſe: nor againſt the ſtroake of ſo leaden a ſword, vſe the protection of ſo golden a ſhield. A little aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd Stoiciſme ſhall ſerue the turne; and with a Secure Contempt, I'le let them Scoule alowd Vnheard. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine</hi> BARTEN HOLYDAY,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:8"/>
            <head>A LETTER OF A JVDICIOVS FRIEND requested by the Authour to deliver his cenſure on his Tranſlation.</head>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. B.H. I haue read your ſmooth tranſlation of rough <hi>Perſius,</hi> and ſend it home to you with my Cenſure (ſuch as you wiſh) ingenuouſly free. I will deale Iuſtly with you Now, Friendly at Other times. In My judgement, when you converſed in this familiar and friendly manner with <hi>Perſius</hi> his Satires, your witte ſtooped farre below the elevation of its owne worth. But as <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſaid of <hi>Claudian</hi> and his works, <hi>Solo argumento ignobiliore oppreſſus addit de ingenio, quantum deeſt materiae: (Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Poetic:)</hi> So I of You and Your Poem; Whatſoever is meane in your Authour, is (mee thinkes) ſo choicely adorned by Your <hi>Genius:</hi> that if it ſtand out of the preſence of Ignorance or Deſperat Emulation, it may bee Gracefull. Which I doe more hartily affirme, becauſe you haue Chaſtiſed your Poet with modeſt, yet ſignificant termes: where ſome ranke-breathed Interpretet would haue rendred him with a ſtrong ſavour of laſciviouſneſſe. I know not now, what ſhould ſtay You from ſending it abroad, or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from giuing it welcome entertainment. If Old <hi>Perſius</hi> were ever worth the hauing: Yours, I doubt not, will bee thought Well worth the reading; yet looke for Other cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Neglect them. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend, <hi>IOHN LEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:8"/>
            <div type="encomium">
               <lg>
                  <l>DArke <hi>Perſius, Ambroſe</hi> threw thy booke on ground</l>
                  <l>With indignation, 'cauſe 'twas ſo profound:</l>
                  <l>But now in <hi>fathers</hi> roome a <hi>child</hi> is ſprung,</l>
                  <l>That reader thy Satires in a vulgar tongue.</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> yet with ambroſe to be fed,</l>
                  <l>That could ſo wiſely tracke, where thou couldſt tred,</l>
                  <l>He takes away thy vaile, and makes that line</l>
                  <l>Tranſalpine, which the <hi>Romans</hi> would confine:</l>
                  <l>Now let thy wandring ſhadow freely roaue,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeke great place in the <hi>Eliſian</hi> groaue,</l>
                  <l>Where ſince theres ſtore of bay, for him one knit,</l>
                  <l>That makes the looſer <hi>Brytaines</hi> feare thy wit.</l>
                  <l>Needes muſt his <hi>owne</hi> inventions <hi>radiant</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>That caſts <hi>ſuch beames</hi> through <hi>thy opacitie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hence forth (bright <hi>Holyday</hi>) to change refuſe</l>
                  <l>Thine Owne <hi>Terpſichore,</hi> with tranſlated Muſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In</hi> Latio <hi>latuit</hi> Saturnum <hi>filius:</hi> Aulum</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic poterat ſoboles iſta latere ſuum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ante tuas</hi> (Holydaie) <hi>faces; hâc luce refulget</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pluribus, &amp; caeco, tector ante, patri.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gymnaſiarcha, puer, feſtivus ludat vterque:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Per</hi> Feſtum <hi>vobis otia quanta diem?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nunquam</hi> Pegaſeas <hi>libavit</hi> Perſius <hi>vndas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nee fonte, &amp;c. Nec in bic: &amp;c.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aut clauſit docto lumina pigra jugo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nempe</hi> tibi, <hi>fontem laticeſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; culmina</hi> Phoebus</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Servârat: pleno dum ſatur ore mades.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quidve</hi> Aulus <hi>traheret? cum fic</hi> Helicona <hi>refundas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vt natet</hi> Angligenis Jtala Muſa labris.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>IOHN WALL.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VPON THE HAPPY TRANSLATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the moſt difficult <hi>Satiriſt,</hi> performed by <hi>his deare friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. B. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Sing the Conqueſt, which an <hi>Engliſh</hi> rime,</l>
               <l>With all its force ne're wonne before This Time.</l>
               <l>Who thought that there would extant be the Man</l>
               <l>That ſuch ſtiffe, ſullen, hardy <hi>Romans can</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Subdue, and with an hand, learnedly fierce,</l>
               <l>Bind in the fetters of a <hi>Britane</hi> verſe?</l>
               <l>Yet here is one that doth: But not as thoſe</l>
               <l>That <note n="*" place="margin">Ovid: Met. Virg: Aeneid.</note> 
                  <hi>changed ſhapes,</hi> and <hi>wandring Trojans</hi> choſe</l>
               <l>For to tranſlate, with lines a mile in length,</l>
               <l>Or Paraphraſe that tires. Such is His ſtrength</l>
               <l>And ſtrictneſſe, he his Author without wrong</l>
               <l>Lodges in priſons but of fiue foot long.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some</hi> I haue knowne, that did Attempt the ſame</l>
               <l>Which that they Durſt, it was their Greateſt fame,</l>
               <l>But it was He, that could diſdaine to ſtay</l>
               <l>At this praiſe Margent, only to Aſſay:</l>
               <l>He with impetuous and all-conquering wit</l>
               <l>That only had the power to finiſh it.</l>
               <l>For had They don't, J know they muſt haue left</l>
               <l>Their graver ſtudies, and haue filcht with theft</l>
               <l>Guiltie of too much ſacriledge, more howres,</l>
               <l>Then time would looſe; or elſe thoſe ſiſter powers</l>
               <l>Jnvoke to lend them <hi>Others liues,</hi> to plucke</l>
               <l>A veſſell with ſuch <hi>Remora's</hi> beſtucke</l>
               <l>To wiſhed ſhoare. But as for Him, with ſtrange</l>
               <l>And eaſie haſt, he did his <hi>Roman</hi> change</l>
               <l>Without complaint of time: No ſerious part</l>
               <l>Of learning murmur'd, that he did impart</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:3"/>Howres to the worke. For all this was begot</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(I ſpeake my conſcience)</hi> when it was his lot</l>
               <l>To be at Truce with ſtudie. Then iudge you</l>
               <l>That ſhall vpon his happy paines, a vew</l>
               <l>Beſtow, that nere the <hi>Muſes Holydaies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or times of leaſure, were with greater Praiſe,</l>
               <l>Or Thrift, or Buſineſſe ſpent: and likewiſe ſince</l>
               <l>He conquer'd hath ſo fierce a <hi>Latin</hi> Prince</l>
               <l>Vnto the Rimes and Phraſes of Our tongue:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Decree that bayes vnto his brow belong.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. WHITE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>TO HIS KIND FRIEND M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>B. H.</hi> vpon his <hi>Perſius.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>AS if in travailes farre ingag'd, at laſt</l>
               <l>Return'd, I gratulate thy labours paſt.</l>
               <l>But when vnto thy waies I turne mine eye</l>
               <l>Dangers obſcur'd with dangers J eſpie.</l>
               <l>J think't a taske too great for humane ſleights,</l>
               <l>Vngraueld or vndaſht to paſſe thoſe ſtreights.</l>
               <l>Admiring thy chaſt notes, in which vnharmd</l>
               <l>The <hi>Syrens</hi> luſtfull language thou haſt charm'd.</l>
               <l>That Art I loue, when as 'gainſt faith of ſence</l>
               <l>By ſence of faith I ſee things flow from thence.</l>
               <l>Nor doe I (like to his ore'wheeling braine)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perſius</hi> ſtill a cloud, imbrace in vaine;</l>
               <l>This's the ſubſtance giues vice the fatall blow</l>
               <l>The others thunder few to feare doe know.</l>
               <l>On envy, ſummon all the vices ſpight:</l>
               <l>Better they ſhould be conquer'd then not Fight.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. WELDON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:4"/>
               <head>VNTO HIS LOVING FRIEND M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>B. H.</hi> vpon <hi>Perſius</hi> tranſlated.</head>
               <l>THis worke me thinkes makes my coniecture bold</l>
               <l>T' affirme th' <hi>Athenians</hi> paradox is true,<note place="margin">Annus Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicus.</note>
               </l>
               <l>When by yeares revolution J behold</l>
               <l>Men dead reviue, things long ſince old, grow new.</l>
               <l>For ſhould dead <hi>Rome</hi> awake, and thoſe looſe times</l>
               <l>Which feard and felt this ſcourging Satiriſt,</l>
               <l>Shee might againe in vs review her crimes;</l>
               <l>As fertile is Our age. Nor hath it miſt</l>
               <l>The worſt of all Her ills. Vainely we thought</l>
               <l>Thy aſhes <hi>(Perſius)</hi> Slept within thine vrne:</l>
               <l>Feard not thy laſh: hop't negligence had wrought</l>
               <l>Thy lines worſe Funerall: and at length would turne</l>
               <l>All to obſcuritie; For how few did ſtriue</l>
               <l>T' enlighten thy darke phraſe, vnleſſe ſome vice</l>
               <l>Made an acute bad comment: So to thriue</l>
               <l>And purchaſe perspicuitie, is a price</l>
               <l>Thou would'ſt haue griev'd to giue. Yet ſince in ill</l>
               <l>We haue ore'tune paſt times: I muſt reioyce</l>
               <l>That Conſtant induſtrie ſhould get ſuch skill</l>
               <l>As to tell vs our bad in <hi>Perſius</hi> voice:</l>
               <l>Whom now All vnderſtand: all may endure</l>
               <l>To reade, but Such as would their crimes obſcure.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. GOFFE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>TO THE AVTHOR HIS moſt loued friend.</head>
               <l>VVHat None haue Dar'd, Thou haſt; and might'ſt againe</l>
               <l>With praiſe, were it vndar'd. Did'ſt thou abſtaine</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:4"/>Yet longer, none would dare Thee to Prevent;</l>
               <l>If any, what could breed thy more Content</l>
               <l>Then, when by victorie, thy glory ſhould</l>
               <l>Be doubled? yea, although recall ſome could,</l>
               <l>From fields of reſt, thy <hi>Perſius</hi> to conſult:</l>
               <l>Yet would no leſſe praiſe from thy lines reſult,</l>
               <l>Then that vnparalel'd, which now is due</l>
               <l>From thoſe that reade thee. Who when they ſhall view</l>
               <l>How Truely with thine Author thou doſt pace</l>
               <l>How hand in hand yee goe, what equall grace</l>
               <l>Thou doſt with him obſerue in every tearme:</l>
               <l>They cannot, but, if iuſt, iuſtly affirme:</l>
               <l>That did your Times as doe your Lines agree,</l>
               <l>He might be thought to haue tranſlated Thee;</l>
               <l>But that he's Darker, not ſo Strong; Wherein</l>
               <l>Thy Greater art more clearely may be ſeene;</l>
               <l>Which doſt thy <hi>Perſius</hi> clowdie ſtormes display</l>
               <l>With lightning and with thunder; Both which lay</l>
               <l>Couched perchance in him, but wanted force</l>
               <l>To breake, or light from darkneſſe to divorce;</l>
               <l>Till Thine Exhaled skill compreſs'd it ſo,</l>
               <l>That forc'd the clouds to breake, the light to ſhew,</l>
               <l>The thunder to be heard. That now each child</l>
               <l>Can prattle what was meant: whil'ſt Thou art ſtil'd</l>
               <l>Of all, with titles of true dignitie,</l>
               <l>For Loftie Phraſe, and perspicuitie.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I. KNIGHT.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:5"/>
               <head>TO THE AVTHOR HIS very good friend.</head>
               <l>RE-liuing <hi>Perſius,</hi> Daies-Birth, Heire of Fame:</l>
               <l>I wrong not <hi>Perſius,</hi> giuing Thee His name;</l>
               <l>If any, I wrong thee for what He did</l>
               <l>Had'ſt Thou him not Illuſtred, had beene hid.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This</hi> being but thy <hi>Pedeſtall</hi> of praiſe,</l>
               <l>Oh what a <hi>Pyramis</hi> will thy <hi>Next</hi> worke raiſe?</l>
               <l>True Laureat, with bleſt Omens goe thou on;</l>
               <l>All-imitable, imitating none.</l>
               <l>I speake not this (nor need'ſt thou it) of Favour.</l>
               <l>But as one conſcious of thy Great workes labour.</l>
               <l>My tongue was never oil'd i'th' baſe claw-art.</l>
               <l>Jn Others read thou Wit, in Me my Heart.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>TO HIS LEARNED FRIEND M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B. H.</hi> vpon his iudicious tranſlation of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>VVHat lay impriſon'd, and confin'd alone</l>
               <l>Only to deeper apprehenſion;</l>
               <l>Thy more benigne, ſublim'd, tranſcendent wit</l>
               <l>Hath reacht, and conquer'd, and imparted it.</l>
               <l>And giu'n't to all, which makes it more thine owne</l>
               <l>Since all are heires of that invention.</l>
               <l>Nor doth one iot, ſo ſweete congruitie,</l>
               <l>Adulterate the <hi>Latin</hi> chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>All things conſeru'd, ſo terſe, <hi>ſo nothing loſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:9"/>As if thou didſt conſult with th' Authors Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch height, ſuch ſacred indignation</l>
               <l>As ſeemes a <hi>Perſius,</hi> no Tranſlation.</l>
               <l>On, learned Quill; thus vindicate thy name</l>
               <l>From times prowd Iniurie, Traytor to fame:</l>
               <l>Nor ſuffer yet, that <hi>Italy</hi> ſo long</l>
               <l>Should make her Vice ſpeake <hi>Engliſh,</hi> not her Tong.</l>
               <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip backe her baſiards, ſend them home to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let her that was their parent, be their tombe.</l>
               <l>Meane while J dare Congratulate our Crimes</l>
               <l>Made Happy that they could produce Theſe Rimes.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. G.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:10"/>
            <head>AVLVS PERSIVS FLACCVS. THE PROLOGVE.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>Need and not Inſpired skill</l>
               <l>Makes our Author trie his quill.</l>
            </argument>
            <l>MY lippes did never touch the ſpring</l>
            <l>Of the wing'd horſe: nor can I bring</l>
            <l>To minde, that e're I dream'd vpon</l>
            <l>Two-topt <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> that thereon</l>
            <l>I might be' Inspir'd and So Vp-ſtart</l>
            <l>A Poet by Infuſed art.</l>
            <l>And all the <hi>Muſes</hi> that doe dwell</l>
            <l>'Bout pale <hi>Pirene,</hi> and the well</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Helicon,</hi> to Thoſe I leaue,</l>
            <l>Vnto whoſe ſtatue's browes doth cleaue</l>
            <l>The Jvy-greene incircling Crowne.</l>
            <l>In humbleneſſe I halfe a Clowne</l>
            <l>Doe only bring this my rude line,</l>
            <l>Vnto <hi>Apollo's</hi> ſacred ſhrine.</l>
            <l>Yet blame me not for my bold deed:</l>
            <l>Alas! I write enforc'd by <note n="a" place="margin">A ſatirical Ironie <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> was a Knight of <hi>Rome</hi> of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient wealth.</note> need.</l>
            <l>Who taught the Parrot his kind <hi>Haile?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who taught the Pie ſo to prevaile</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:11"/>To frame Our words? 'Twas but to fill</l>
            <l>Their belly, maſter of their skill;</l>
            <l>Which skilfull is to make them reach</l>
            <l>Voices, which Nature cannot teach.</l>
            <l>Nay; if there chance to ſhine but ſome</l>
            <l>Hope, of deceitfull Gaine to come:</l>
            <l>Crow-poets and poetique Pies</l>
            <l>You'd thinke did chaunt ſweet ayries;</l>
            <l>And make (when as they harſhly Crie)</l>
            <l>A <hi>Pegaſeian</hi> Melodie.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="satire">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SATIRE. 1.</hi> THE FIRST SATIRE IN forme of a Dialogue. <hi>The Speakers. PERSIVS. MONITOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>Inſpired poets Art and Pride</l>
               <l>Our Satiriſt doth heere deride.</l>
            </argument>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>O Cares of men! O emptie Vanitie</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">Out of the too abundant varietie of the interpunctions of theſe three verſes following, I could find none more accurate, then this I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and here vſed.</note>Why?</l>
               <l>Of things!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>who'l read theſe Wondring Satires?</l>
               <l>Doſt Thou ſay ſo my Friend?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>Faith I thinke none.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>How ſaiſt thou? None?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>Perchance ſome two, or—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>None?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>Tis hard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet why? Leaſt <hi>Rome's</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="bottom">Ironically here the Poet cals <hi>Nero Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydamas</hi> who is much famouſed by <hi>Homer</hi> in diverſe places for his vertue, yea and compared with <hi>Hector. Iliad.</hi> μ.</note> 
                     <hi>Polydamas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And doutie <hi>Troians</hi> ſhould preferre the aſſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="bottom">A ridiculous Poet, that tranſlated fiue bookes of <hi>Homers Iliads</hi> into verſe, word for word, with extreame obſcuritie, and no leſſe abſurditie.</note> 
                     <hi>Labeo</hi> before Mee? Tuſh; their falſe doome</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:12"/>Is but a trifle. If diſturbed <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prowdly ſleight any thing, ſcorne to deſcend</l>
                  <l>To Their Vaine cenſure: neither ſtriue to mend</l>
                  <l>The tongue of thy falſe ballance in Their ſcale</l>
                  <l>Which is as wrong: but if thou'dſt never faile</l>
                  <l>Know This: <hi>To trie thy ſecret innocence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſureſt witneſſe is thy conſcience.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Who is Not at <hi>Rome?</hi> O that I might</l>
                  <l>But freely ſpeake, yet ſpeake no more then Right.</l>
                  <l>And So I May. Then, when I caſt mine eie</l>
                  <l>On thoſe whoſe Faces promiſe Gravitie:</l>
                  <l>On our ſad <hi>Stoickes:</hi> on the things we doe</l>
                  <l>Since we left off to play with nuts: and view</l>
                  <l>Our actions, when we labour much to be</l>
                  <l>Sterne Vnckles. Then! then! But, oh, pardon me,</l>
                  <l>I will not touch. Yet can I hold my peace</l>
                  <l>Vrg'd Thus? and from revenge ſo luſt, Thus ceaſe?</l>
                  <l>I'me of a Scoffing ſpleene. I Loue to Flout</l>
                  <l>At Hypocrites: therefore it now Muſt out.</l>
                  <l>Then Thus.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Being immur'd from each mans ſight</l>
                  <l>In ſome obſcure retired place, we write</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some,</hi> ev'n-pac'd numbers, <hi>Some</hi> freefooted proſe,</l>
                  <l>Some weighty thing, which th' Author ſtrongly blowes</l>
                  <l>From his large-winded lungs. For he rehearſes</l>
                  <l>Vnto the people ſtraight his well-pen'd verſes;</l>
                  <l>His haire being firſt kemb'd ſmooth, and then he dight,</l>
                  <l>In a faire comely garment freſh and white,</l>
                  <l>Wearing ſome precious jewell, which ſome friend</l>
                  <l>On's birth-day to him for a gift did ſend,</l>
                  <l>With moiſt'ning ſyrrope having clear'd his throat</l>
                  <l>Apt Now to ſound it in a various note.</l>
                  <l>Then is he reading in a ſeat on high,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:12"/>Diſſolu'd vnto a luſtfull <hi>Acting</hi> eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where thou maiſt ſee ev'n thoſe that beare the name</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Rome's</hi> braue <hi>Titi</hi> (but vnto their ſhame)</l>
                  <l>To ſhake with trembling luſt, and to reioice</l>
                  <l>Obſcenely, with a broken skreaking voice</l>
                  <l>When a leud line their inward loines doth pierce,</l>
                  <l>And touch them with a luſt-provoking verſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But thou Old Dotard, doſt Thou ſtriue to feed</l>
                  <l>Other men's eares? nay, Theirs who without heed</l>
                  <l>Or moderate diſcretion praiſe thee ſo,</l>
                  <l>That (skinne-peel'd Aſſe!) thy ſelfe doſt firſt cry, Hoe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Here the Poet faineth a reply of this old am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Poet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> Why did I learne vnleſſe this leaven here</l>
                  <l>Inbred, this ſtrong wild-figtree <hi>ſhould appeare?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And from its ſeate the liver breaking forth</l>
                  <l>Shew to the world its owne, though vnknowne worth?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>O ſee ambitious paleneſſe! ſee Old Age!</l>
               <l>At ſuch corrupted times Who could not rage?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Think'ſt thou, thou nothing know'ſt, if it be ſo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That others knowe not, that thou this dost know?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">A ſecond reply.</note> O but tis braue to heare men cry, <hi>See, ſee?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And pointing with their fingers, ſay, <hi>That's he.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Say you 'had a poeme which ſo ſmoothly runs,</l>
               <l>That 'twere for lectures read to great mens ſons,</l>
               <l>Braue lads with curled lockes, like gold ſo yellow:</l>
               <l>Would not you thinke your ſelfe a pretty fellow?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O that's not all! See, our <hi>Romulidans</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prophane our ſacred poems with foule hands!</l>
                  <l>Reading, amidſt their bowles, poems divine,</l>
                  <l>Being full vp to the throat with fleſh and wine.</l>
                  <l>Where if forſooth one clad in purple cloth's,</l>
                  <l>Snaffle ſome muſtie ſtuffe through's muffling noſe</l>
                  <l>Melting forth faire <hi>Hypſipyle's</hi> ſad ſong</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Phyllis</hi> fortune with a moiſt'ned tong</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:13"/>Or ſome ſuch tales which poetrie affordes</l>
                  <l>His daintie palate tripping forth his wordes,</l>
                  <l>The Men aſſent! And are not th' aſhes then</l>
                  <l>Of this Rare poet bleſt? This man of men</l>
                  <l>Hath he not now a <note n="f" place="bottom">The Ancient Ethniques did vſe to pray that the tombe-ſtones of their dead friends might be light vnto them; becauſe they beleeued that their <hi>Manes</hi> or ſoules remained in their ſepulchers, and were ſenſible of ſuch accidents. They held likewiſe the ſpringing of flowers from the graue of a deceaſed friend, an argument of his happineſſe.</note> lighter mole of earth</l>
                  <l>Gently preſſing his bones? A gen'rall mirth</l>
                  <l>Enſues: the gueſt with hands and voices ring</l>
                  <l>His due applauſe; And ſhall there not now ſpring</l>
                  <l>Ev'n from his <hi>Manes,</hi> from the hollow wombe</l>
                  <l>Of his thriſe-happy vrne-incloſing tombe</l>
                  <l>Sweet Violets? But, Oh, ſaies one, you touch</l>
                  <l>Too ſcoffingly, wrinkling your noſe Too much.</l>
                  <l>For doth there breath a man that can reiect</l>
                  <l>A gen'rall praiſe? and his owne lines neglect?</l>
                  <l>Lines worth immortall Cedars recompence,</l>
                  <l>Nere fearing new-ſold Fiſh or Frankincenſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well; whoſoe're thou art whom I did make</l>
                  <l>But now, the Adverſe part to vndertake;</l>
                  <l>When I my ſelfe doe write, if from my braine</l>
                  <l>Doe flow by greateſt chance ſome happy ſtraine</l>
                  <l>(For tis by chance) My heart is not ſo hard</l>
                  <l>So hornie, as to feare the due reward,</l>
                  <l>Of deſeru'd fame. Only I doe denie</l>
                  <l>The ſcope of vertuous actions to lie</l>
                  <l>In thy <hi>O braue! O fine!</hi> for ſearch but this</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>O fine!</hi> and within it What not is?</l>
                  <l>No; in Theſe papers knowe thou ſhalt not find</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Labeo's</hi> helleborated lines confin'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:13"/>Too ſuperſtitiouſly to Words: nor weake</l>
                  <l>Loue-elegies, ſuch as <hi>Rome's</hi> Nobles ſpeake:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe iudgement like their overcharged maw,</l>
                  <l>Wants ſtrong concoctions heat, &amp; is Yet raw.</l>
                  <l>Briefly whatſe're on <note n="g" place="bottom">The <hi>Romans</hi> had their <hi>lecti lucubratorii</hi> on which they ſtudied, and <hi>tricliniares,</hi> on which they eate the latter are rather vnderſtood in this place, for he principally ſpeaketh againſt the verſes they writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their cupps.</note> Citrean beds is writ,</l>
                  <l>We hence exclude as th' excrement of wit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou doſt ſome diſh of good hot meate provide</l>
                  <l>For ſome poore wretch (whoſe bellie's his tongues guid)</l>
                  <l>Or to thy quaking foll'wer thou doſt caſt</l>
                  <l>Thy thread-bare cloake (which could no longer laſt)</l>
                  <l>Then thus thou ſpeak'ſt. You knowe ev'n from my youth</l>
                  <l>I hated lies, now therefore tell me truth.</l>
                  <l>Of me (P. Can He tell truth? Wilt let Me ſpeake?</l>
                  <l>Thou trifleſt (bald-pate aſſe!) and thy skill's weake.</l>
                  <l>Seeing a fat-hogge-trough-panch before thee ſtruts</l>
                  <l>Full Eighteene inches with a load of guts.</l>
                  <l>O bleſſed <hi>Ianus!</hi> happy is Thy lucke!</l>
                  <l>Behind <note n="h" place="bottom">Three manner of flouts were vſed by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients. The firſt was with their hand to make a Storkes bill, their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers being all collected together, and then let out with a flurt. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond was to put their thumbes to the temples of their heads, and then wagge their fingers like aſſes eares, which within are ſomewhat white. The third was to lill out their tongues, like dogges in the heate of ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, especially in hot countries, ſuch as is <hi>Apulia</hi> a region in <hi>Italie.</hi>
                     </note> thy backe, whom never Storkes bill ſtrucke:</l>
                  <l>At whom no nimble finger'd hand being fram'd</l>
                  <l>Like aſſes white eares, ever Yet was aim'd:</l>
                  <l>Nor ſo much tongue thruſt forth in a baſe flout</l>
                  <l>As an <hi>Apulian</hi> bitch for thirſt lils out.</l>
                  <l>You O <hi>Patrician</hi> blood whoſe heads are blind</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:14"/>I'th' hinder part, prevent a ſcorne behind.)</l>
                  <l>What doe men ſay?<note n="i" place="margin">The anſwere of the flatteres</note> That now your verſes flow</l>
                  <l>In a ſoft number'd pace both ſweet and ſlow,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe well-ſmooth'd parts are ſo exactly join'd</l>
                  <l>That the ſevereſt naile can never finde</l>
                  <l>The leaſt vnev'neſſe. O ſaies one, he makes</l>
                  <l>A verſe, as he that his true levell takes,</l>
                  <l>Shutting one eye, for to direct his line,</l>
                  <l>Which drawing, with red oaker he doth ſigne.</l>
                  <l>Whether he ſcourge with his deepe-wounding rimes</l>
                  <l>The delicate ſoft manners of the times,</l>
                  <l>Or th'impious banquets of revenging Kings:</l>
                  <l>Our Poets <hi>Muſe</hi> can well expreſſe great things.</l>
                  <l>P. I, You ſhall ſee a fellow dare aſſay</l>
                  <l>To write Heroicke acts, who th' other day</l>
                  <l>But trifel'd out ſome Fables of ſmall worth</l>
                  <l>In ſcarce true <hi>Greeke:</hi> whoſe skill cannot paint forth</l>
                  <l>A pleaſant ſelfe-deſcribing Groue's delights;</l>
                  <l>Nor praiſe the full-ſtor'd Country, that ev'n writes</l>
                  <l>The ſtory of its Owne abundant ſtore;</l>
                  <l>Where fruits and fire-wood and the fat'ned Boare</l>
                  <l>Are never wanting; where the ſhepheards feaſt</l>
                  <l>Sacred to <hi>Pales</hi> is, t' expell the beaſt</l>
                  <l>That hates the lambe: where ſhepheards on that day</l>
                  <l>Are purged in a fire of ſmoaking hay.</l>
                  <l>Whence <hi>Remus</hi> ſprung: where (<note n="k" place="margin">Q. Cincinnatus.</note> 
                     <hi>Quintius</hi>) thou waſt borne,</l>
                  <l>And where thy plow-ſhare was in furrowes worne;</l>
                  <l>When as thy wife trembling with ioy and feare,</l>
                  <l>Made thee the great <hi>Dictators</hi> roabes to weare</l>
                  <l>Before thine Oxen, and to leaue them Now,</l>
                  <l>Making the <hi>Lictor</hi> carry home thy plow.</l>
                  <l>Behold then this braue Poet.</l>
                  <l>Some there are</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:14"/>To whom <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Furius Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Labeo. Briſeus,</hi> is the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> fitly heere attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to <hi>Labeo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his mad verſes.</note> 
                     <hi>Briſean Labeo's</hi> book ſeemes rare:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe lines ſwell like full Veines. Others deſire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pacuvius,</hi> whom much they doe admire,</l>
                  <l>And loue often to reade, and ev'n to ſtay</l>
                  <l>Vpon his knottie harſh <hi>Antiopa;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe wofull heart was nouriſhed with greefe,</l>
                  <l>The Depth of ſorrow yeelding Some releefe.</l>
                  <l>When thou ſhalt ſee the blear-eied father teach</l>
                  <l>His ſon theſe things; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thou not quickly reach</l>
                  <l>To know the cauſe how this our vile diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>This hiſſing frying-pan of Speach tooke place</l>
                  <l>Firſt, in our to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues? And yet wherin our ſmooth</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">The Knights of <hi>Rome</hi> were anciently ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſurpriſed a towne in <hi>Hetruria</hi> called <hi>Troſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulum,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>
                     <hi>Troſſulians</hi> vainely themſelues doe ſooth,</l>
                  <l>And ev'n leape in their ſeats, when as they heare</l>
                  <l>Old words, which pleaſe their thick falſe-judging eare.</l>
                  <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'art accus'd, art not aſham'd to be</l>
                  <l>Not able thy now-Aged head to free</l>
                  <l>From feare o'th 'law, but loue the luke-warm cry</l>
                  <l>Of all thy hearers crying, <hi>Decently?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedius</hi> ſayes one, vnto thy charge I lay</l>
                  <l>The guilt of theft. What now doth <hi>Pedius</hi> ſay?</l>
                  <l>In ſmooth <hi>Antitheta's</hi> his fault he weighes,</l>
                  <l>And for his learned Figures, winnes much praiſe.</l>
                  <l>O neate! O neate? In judging thou doſt faile,</l>
                  <l>Baſe fawning <hi>Romane,</hi> doſt thou wagge thy taile?</l>
                  <l>For think'ſt thou, if ſome ſhip-wrack'd wretch ſhould Sing.</l>
                  <l>Hee e're from me one Halfe-peny ſhould wring?</l>
                  <l>Doſt Sing, when at thy ſhoulder thou doſt weare</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe and ſhippe, which the ſharpe rocks did teare?</l>
                  <l>His teares ſhall be expreſs'd through's Miſerie,</l>
                  <l>Not-Studi'd for by Night, that would mooue Mee</l>
                  <l>To pitie. M. Yet in Numbers, O, there ſhines</l>
                  <l>Beauteous compoſure added to thoſe lines</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:15"/>Which were before but raw. <hi>P.</hi> I, ſo it ſeemes;</l>
                  <l>For one, this as the only skill eſteemes</l>
                  <l>To end his verſe (But, O ridiculous!)</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Berecinthian Atys;</hi> or els, thus;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Dolphin which did cut Cerulean Nereus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ex'lent! and this our <hi>Romans</hi> count moſt ſerious!</l>
                  <l>So thus another drawes his numbred line,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We drew a ribbe from the long Apennine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Virgils Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neads, <hi>which beginne ſo,</hi> Arma vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cano.</note>
                  <hi>Armes, and the man I ſing,</hi> perchance you'l dare</l>
               <l>To terme This frothy, fat-bark'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>O no; ſpare</l>
               <l>Your Too-quicke cenſure, &amp; diſſolue your brow.</l>
               <l>This Poem as an aged well-growne bough</l>
               <l>Seaſon'd with time, is with the warme Suns heat</l>
               <l>Well boild in its owne barke; growne ſtrong and great.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>What then doe you terme ſoft, and to be read</l>
               <l>With a looſe-bending necke, and bow'd-downe head?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their writh'd hornes the Mimallones did fill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With ſounds, and Baſſaris about to kill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſcornefull calfe, ſnatching from him his head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Moenas as the ſpotted Lynx ſhee lead</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With Joy-bridles, oft did Evion ſound:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The reparable Eccho did rebound.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe, theſe are braue I But, Oh, ſhould Such lines be</l>
               <l>If any veine of Old Nobilitie</l>
               <l>Did liue in vs? Theſe Weake lines in the Brimme</l>
               <l>Of ev'ry mouth, in th'vtmoſt ſpittle ſwimme.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moenas</hi> and <hi>Atys</hi> or ſome fooliſh Songes</l>
               <l>Are alwaies in the moiſture of their tongues.</l>
               <l>They never Buffeted a Deske for Theſe,</l>
               <l>Or Bitte their Nailes: ſuch lines are writte with eaſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <l>Grant this be true: yet Sir You haue no need</l>
               <l>With biting truth to make their ſoft eares bleed.</l>
               <l>Well, looke you to't; I feare; be not too bold,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:15"/>Leſt great mens threſholds towards you grow cold.</l>
               <l>Me thinkes, th' are touch'd already, and I heare,</l>
               <l>The doggiſh letter R ſound in mine eare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, Sir, rather then ſo, all's white and free:</l>
               <l>All, all is admirable well for Mee.</l>
               <l>I will not hinder't. Now y'are pleas'd I thinke.</l>
               <l>You'l ſay, Let no man make My verſes ſtinke,</l>
               <l>Making a place for <note n="o" place="margin">This place is thus againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation more manerly and truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Bond.</hi>
                  </note> vrine, in a ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Among My papers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>See then you adorne</l>
               <l>Your booke, and paint two <note n="p" place="margin">Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the <hi>Genius</hi> of the place, and were painted there to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre anie from viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the place by any pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Serpents on't; Boyes, None</l>
               <l>Muſt vrine in This Sacred place: be gone:</l>
               <l>And Ile goe firſt.</l>
               <l>Yet did <hi>Lucilius</hi> cut</l>
               <l>Lewd <hi>Rome,</hi> and thee, O <hi>Lupus,</hi> that didſt glut</l>
               <l>Thy appetite, and thee <hi>(Mutius)</hi> growne weake</l>
               <l>With luſt, &amp; did on vs his Iaw-tooth breake.</l>
               <l>So ſubtile <hi>Horace</hi> laughing with his friend</l>
               <l>Would cunningly his vices reprehend,</l>
               <l>And lying in his boſome, in his heart,</l>
               <l>Would bitterly deride him with great art.</l>
               <l>Skilfull he was baſely t'eſteeme the rout,</l>
               <l>Yet neere wrinkled his noſe, or Seem'd to flout.</l>
               <l>And may not I then <hi>Mutter?</hi> not to th' <note n="q" place="margin">An alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Midas.</hi>
                  </note> Duſt?</l>
               <l>Not, though Alone? No where? I will; I muſt</l>
               <l>Digge here, ev'n here. (My book) I ſpeak to Thee;</l>
               <l>I'ue ſeene, I ſay, I'ue ſeene; (my tong's born free)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who has not Aſſes eares?</hi> Thou ſhalt not buy</l>
               <l>This my obſcure concealed myſterie,</l>
               <l>This my dear ſcoffe, my <hi>Nothing,</hi> for whole miliads</l>
               <l>Of any baſe Poets long-winded <hi>Iliads.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou whoſo'ere thou art, that art inſpir'd</l>
               <l>With bold <hi>Cratinus;</hi> or with zeale art fir'd</l>
               <l>Like angry <hi>Eupolis;</hi> and art growne pale</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:16"/>With that <note n="r" place="margin">Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes.</note> old man, whoſe ſtile with a full ſaile</l>
               <l>Beares ſtrong againſt foule vice: vouchſafe a glance</l>
               <l>On theſe My Satires alſo; where by chance</l>
               <l>If any thing more perfect thou ſhalt heare,</l>
               <l>Among my lines; grow hot with a purg'd eare.</l>
               <l>But him with deepeſt ſcorne I doe deteſt</l>
               <l>That baſely loues to breake a bitter jeſt</l>
               <l>At a Philoſophers poore Shooe: and winkes</l>
               <l>At him, whoſe ſight is bad, calling him Blinkes:</l>
               <l>Counting himſelfe no meane man, bearing ſome</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jtalian</hi> honour at <hi>Aretium;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Cauſe, being Market-Clarke (ſuch was his pleaſure)</l>
               <l>He brake their earthen veſſels leſſe then meaſure.</l>
               <l>Nor loue I him that counts the counting-table</l>
               <l>Of deepe <hi>Arithmeticians</hi> but a fable.</l>
               <l>Nor him that ſcoffes at Figures made in <note n="ſ" place="margin">An alluſion to the ſtory of <hi>Archimedes;</hi> ſee <hi>Plutarch's Marcellus.</hi>
                  </note> duſt</l>
               <l>By ſound <hi>Geometry.</hi> Such are vniuſt,</l>
               <l>And Enimies to th'Arts. They much delight</l>
               <l>To ſee the bold-fac'd queane <hi>Nonaria</hi> fight</l>
               <l>With a good honeſt <hi>Cynicke;</hi> and will grinne</l>
               <l>If that ſhee pull his beard off from his chinne.</l>
               <l>Theſe, in the morning next their hearts Ile ſend</l>
               <l>To ſtudy the Edicts leſt they offend:</l>
               <l>Yet after dinner (for they 'le turne no more</l>
               <l>From vice) vnto <hi>Callirhoe</hi> their Whore.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="satire">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SATIRE. 2. THE SECOND SATIRE VNTO</hi> his friend Plotius Macrinus.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>Profane deſires: true ſacrifice:</l>
               <l>Bold ſinnes: our Poet here deſcries.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>SIgne This day <hi>(Macrine)</hi> with a Purer ſtone,</l>
               <l>Which doth preſent to thee times long ſince gone.</l>
               <l>Powre wine vnto thy <hi>Genius;</hi> for Thy care</l>
               <l>Is not to winne <hi>Ioue</hi> with a Bribing prayer.</l>
               <l>Nor crau'ſt Thou, what thou ſham'ſt to name for feare</l>
               <l>Except <hi>Ioue's</hi> drawne aſide that none may heare.</l>
               <l>Though no ſmall part of <hi>Rome's</hi> chiefe <hi>Nobles</hi> can</l>
               <l>Sacrifice with a <hi>low-voic'd</hi> incenſe-pan.</l>
               <l>Tis not an eaſie thing to take away</l>
               <l>The murmur'd whiſperings of thoſe that pray</l>
               <l>From the Gods Temples. Tis no eaſie thing</l>
               <l>To liue with Knowne deſires. <note n="a" place="bottom">This was but the manner of ſome hypocrites; for it was the Cuſtome of the <hi>Romanes</hi> to pray ſoftly to themſelues, as <hi>Ioſ. Scaliger</hi> well obſerues in his Caſtigations on the <hi>2.</hi> li. of <hi>Tibullus.</hi> p. <hi>137.</hi> &amp; <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werius</hi> in his Animadverſions on <hi>Petronius.</hi> p. 428.</note> They vſe to ſing</l>
               <l>Alowd, that ſtrangers and the ſtanders-by</l>
               <l>May heare 'hem, when they pray for honeſty</l>
               <l>Or a good mind, good fame. But for the reſt</l>
               <l>Of their deſires, inwardly th' are ſuppreſt</l>
               <l>Vnder their murmuring tongues; ſuch as are theſe</l>
               <l>Profane requeſts; O that ſome ſtrong diſeaſe</l>
               <l>Would make my Vnckl's braue rich funerall</l>
               <l>To bubble vp. O that my rake would fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:17"/>As I were working, on ſome ſounding pot</l>
               <l>Of ſilver; <note n="b" place="bottom">Antiquitie made <hi>Hercules</hi> the propitious God for the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of hidden Treaſure.</note> 
                  <hi>Hercules</hi> bleſſing my lot.</l>
               <l>Or would I might expu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge this yong, rich Ward</l>
               <l>By whom from great poſſeſſions I am bar'd</l>
               <l>Being the next heire; for he's with ſcabs perplext,</l>
               <l>And is with ſwelling choller ſharply vext.</l>
               <l>There's <hi>Nereus</hi> to, has buri'd yee three wiues,</l>
               <l>And I ſcarce—! O Such men lead Happy liues!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That theſe things thou religiouſly maiſt craue</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Ioue,</hi> in ſwelling <hi>Tybers</hi> ſilver waue</l>
               <l>Early thou waſheſt twiſe or thrice thy 'head</l>
               <l>Purging the <note n="c" place="bottom">Of this, ſee <hi>Caſaubon</hi> on <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus;</hi> p. <hi>292.</hi> where he ſhews their twofold manner of expiation. And <hi>Briſſonius</hi> at large, lib. <hi>1.</hi> de <hi>Formulis,</hi> p. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> night pollutions of thy bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doſt heare? anſwere me this: and but diſcloſe</l>
               <l>Thy thought in one ſmal queſtion Ile propoſe.</l>
               <l>What thinkſt of <hi>Joue?</hi> thinkſt he may be preferd</l>
               <l>'Fore Some? Whom? be't ev'n <note n="d" place="bottom">A wicked fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that poyſned his brother and brothers wife.</note> 
                  <hi>Staius;</hi> art afeard?</l>
               <l>And doubtſt thou Whether is the fitteſt Guard</l>
               <l>And iuſter iudge for a young guidleſſe Ward?</l>
               <l>This then, wherwith thou dar'ſt to preſſe <hi>Iou's</hi> eare,</l>
               <l>Tell but to <hi>Staius:</hi> would he not ev'n feare</l>
               <l>To heare thee Speake? and caſting vp his eie</l>
               <l>Cry, O good <hi>Joue!</hi> and ſhall not <hi>Joue</hi> then cry</l>
               <l>Vnto himſelfe for vengeance? What? doſt thinke</l>
               <l>Thou art Forgiv'n, becauſe he's pleaſd to Winke</l>
               <l>At thy blacke deedes, and ſooner ſtrikes a Tree,</l>
               <l>With horrid Sulphure, then Thy houſe and Thee,</l>
               <l>When with his roaring thunders he doth chide</l>
               <l>The prowd high-mounting aire? Dar'ſt thou deride</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:17"/>The pow'r of Heav'n, and lay with <hi>Joues</hi> Fond beard,</l>
               <l>As if th'hadſt Leaue, becauſe thou ne're was fear'd.</l>
               <l>With ſome ſtrange judgement? or ne're yet did'ſt lie</l>
               <l>A woefull ſpectacle to each mans eie,</l>
               <l>Vnholy, to be ſhunn'd in ſome ſad groue,</l>
               <l>Then ceaſing to be ſacred vnto <hi>Joue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or th'other Gods, vntill with ſacrifice</l>
               <l>Th'Aruſpex great <hi>Ergenna</hi> purifies</l>
               <l>The ſame, by offring th'entrals of two ſheepe?</l>
               <l>Or els, what iſt? with what reward doſt keepe</l>
               <l>The bribed eares of the corrupted Gods</l>
               <l>That they ſhould only giue indulgent nods</l>
               <l>At thy vaſt crimes? iſt thy fat offering</l>
               <l>Which to their ſacred altars thou doſt bring?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now you ſhall ſee ſome grandames, or fond Aunts,</l>
               <l>Whom womens Fury Superſtition haunts,</l>
               <l>Take vp a tender infant in their armes,</l>
               <l>And being skilfull to depell the harmes.</l>
               <l>Of an <note n="e" place="bottom">Of Faſcination, ſee <hi>Del Rio:</hi> Mag: diſquiſ: l. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> Sect. <hi>1.</hi> and <hi>Ramirez,</hi> in his learned Pentecontarchus, cap. <hi>31.</hi> at large.</note> effaſcinating eie, they'le ſpet</l>
               <l>Vpon their middle finger, and then wet</l>
               <l>With this their purging ſpettle, the childs brow</l>
               <l>And prettie lippes. Then with a humble vow</l>
               <l>Dauncing him in their armes, they'le vainely ſpend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Their poore leane hope, in praying <hi>Ioue</hi> to ſend</l>
               <l>This babe in time to come ſuch happineſſe</l>
               <l>As once wealthy <hi>Licinius</hi> did poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>In fruitfull lands: or ſuch as <hi>Craſſus</hi> held,</l>
               <l>Who for braue houſes, <hi>Rome's</hi> chiefe Lords excell'd.</l>
               <l>They wiſh that Kings and Queenes may be at ſtrife</l>
               <l>To make ev'n their beſt daughter His bleſt wife.</l>
               <l>And as for Maides (ſay they) Yee Gods aboue!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:18"/>O let'hem ſtrongly, ſtrangely fall in loue</l>
               <l>With his rare beautie: and that whereſo'er</l>
               <l>Hee treades, a crimſon roſe may ſpring vp there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Braue! braue! But yet I will not bid My nurſe</l>
               <l>Pray ſo: or if ſhee doe; then Good <hi>Ioue</hi> Curſe</l>
               <l>Her Prayers; Though cloth'd-White ſhee ſtrongly Crie,</l>
               <l>Yet for thine <hi>Owne</hi> ſake, Strongly ſtill Denie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou wiſheſt for firme nerues, and for a ſure</l>
               <l>Sound body, that would healthfully endure</l>
               <l>Vntill Old age; why be it, that thy wiſh</l>
               <l>Is Granted by the Gods; yet thy Large diſh</l>
               <l>And full fat ſaſage make the Gods Delay</l>
               <l>To bleſſe thee, and doe Force good <hi>Ioue</hi> to ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou'd'ſt faine grow rich: yet doſt thou ſacrifice</l>
               <l>An Oxe, (is that the way in wealth to riſe?)</l>
               <l>Then vpon <hi>Mercurie</hi> the God of gaine</l>
               <l>With this thy offering, thus thou cri'ſt amaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let my domeſticke Gods (great Mercury)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Make all things happie in my familie!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bleſſe thou my heards of beaſts, bleſſe thou my lambs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And make my tender yewes the happie damm's</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of many yong-ones.</hi> Mad-man! wilt thou ſee?</l>
               <l>This is impoſſible! It cannot bee!</l>
               <l>When as ſo many heyfers fats doe frie</l>
               <l>In flames of ſacrifice? Yet doth he crie,</l>
               <l>And with his Entrals and his dainetie Cake</l>
               <l>Striues to o'recome, and forcingly will Make</l>
               <l>The Gods to heare; nor yet will hold his peace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now doth my field, now doth my fold encreaſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now twill be giv'n: now, now,</hi> vntill at laſt</l>
               <l>Deceau'd, his great hope prooving but a blaſt:</l>
               <l>His Money in his cheſt may make its moane</l>
               <l>For want of company; yet ſigh alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:18"/>
               <l>If for a gift to Thee ſome friend preſents</l>
               <l>A ſilver goblet, or rich ornaments</l>
               <l>Curiouſly graven in a maſſie bowle</l>
               <l>Of pureſt gold: ſtraightway thy very ſoule</l>
               <l>Is touch'd with a ſtrong paſſion: and thou ſhak'ſt</l>
               <l>Ev'n Droppes from thy <hi>left</hi> breaſt (Vaine heart that qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'st</l>
               <l>Thus with a trembling joy?) Now becauſe gold</l>
               <l>Thus pleaſeth Thee; hence tis that Thou doſt hold,</l>
               <l>The Gods are pleas'd ſo too, and over lai'ſt</l>
               <l>Their ſtatues faces (that thereby thou maiſt</l>
               <l>Procure their favour) with gold purchaſed</l>
               <l>From th'enemie, which was in triumph led.</l>
               <l>For thoſe <note n="f" place="bottom">The braſen Statues of the ſonnes of <hi>Aegyptus,</hi> all, except one, ſlaine by their new wiues the daughters of <hi>Danaus.</hi> Which brothers the <hi>Romans</hi> adored as Gods: and were vainely perſwaded that they ſent dreames vnto men.</note> braſſe-brother-gods that ſend a dreame</l>
               <l>Moſt true, and purg'd from thicke, corrupted fleame,</l>
               <l>Whereby in ſleepe men are diſturb'd, or feard,</l>
               <l>Let thoſe be chiefe, and weare a golden beard.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gold hath the pots of earth, and braſſe diſdaign'd,</l>
               <l>Though vs'd when <hi>Numa,</hi> and good <hi>Saturne</hi> raign'd.</l>
               <l>Gold likewiſe hath expeld the <hi>Veſtall</hi> Vrne:</l>
               <l>Gold doth the <hi>Thuſcan</hi> Earth to Gold now turne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Baſe ſtooping ſoules, that groovle on the Earth,</l>
               <l>In whom there's Nothing teſtifies their birth</l>
               <l>To be from Heav'n!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet, doth not this ſuffice?</l>
               <l>But we muſt bring theſe our iniquities,</l>
               <l>To the Gods Temples, where their pow'rs divine</l>
               <l>Doe dwell; and ev'n profane their holy Shrine?</l>
               <l>As if there could be any thing in theſe</l>
               <l>Infected Carcaſes, the Gods to pleaſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20884:19"/>
               <l>This Fleſh of ours makes vs in vaine to ſpoile</l>
               <l>Sweet <hi>Caſia,</hi> by mixing it with oile</l>
               <l>To make vs ointments. This doth make vs ſtaine</l>
               <l>The ſoft <hi>Calabrian</hi> fleece in Purple graine,</l>
               <l>This makes vs with much art to poliſh well</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mother of Pearle,</hi> drawne from the fiſhes ſhell.</l>
               <l>This from th'vnpurged earth made vs deſire</l>
               <l>To ſtraine out veines of gold by purging fire.</l>
               <l>This ſinnes; and ſinnes; yet perſevers in ſinne.</l>
               <l>But you great Prieſts, tell; what doth gold within</l>
               <l>The holy Temples? ſure, no greater thing</l>
               <l>Then <note n="g" place="bottom">It was acuſtome among the Ancients, for Virgins about to marry to offer their Babies as an enſigne of their Virginities to <hi>Venus,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that by her benefit, ſhortly after, they ſhould haue true Babes of their owne.</note> puppets, which to <hi>Venus</hi> Virgins bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No; let vs ſtriue to bring to th'Gods, that which</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Meſſala's</hi> bleare-eyed ofſpring, from his rich</l>
               <l>Large incenſe-baſon nere could giue; A mind</l>
               <l>By Law and by Religion well confin'd;</l>
               <l>A retir'd ſoule; a heart not ſtained by</l>
               <l>Foule luſt, concoct in Noble honeſtie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This let me bring to th'Gods, and Ile obtaine</l>
               <l>Offring but a Small Cake of ſome Courſe graine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="satire">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:19"/>
            <head>SATIRE 3. THE THIRD SATIRE.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>Yong Gallants Sloth, and their Neglect</l>
               <l>Of Arts, this Satire doth detect.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat Ev'ry day thus long? fie, fie, ariſe:</l>
               <l>See how the cleare light ſhamefully deſcries</l>
               <l>Thy ſloth &amp; through thy windows ſhining bright</l>
               <l>Stretcheth the narow chinks with his broadlight.</l>
               <l>We ſnort till the <note n="a" place="margin">An hypall: for, till the ſhadowe touch the fift line; which is about our Eleven of the clocke. Hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands this of Sun-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als. You may ſee the forme of an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Roman</hi> Sun-Diall, in <hi>Ramirez</hi> his Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cont. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> Fift ſhadow touch the line,</l>
               <l>Enough ev'n to digeſt ſtrong <hi>Falerne</hi> wine.</l>
               <l>Now what doſt doe? The furious dog-ſtars heat</l>
               <l>Vpon the parched corne hath long ſince beat</l>
               <l>With its fierce ſcalding influence, and made</l>
               <l>The beaſts to ſeek the ſpreading <hi>Elmes</hi> cool ſhade</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus the companion of ſome ſlothfull youth</l>
               <l>Does freely chide him. Then ſaith he, in truth</l>
               <l>And iſt ſo late? indeed? ſome body then</l>
               <l>Come preſently and reach my cloths: why when?</l>
               <l>If then no bodie come, Oh how he ſwels,</l>
               <l>And breaks with <note n="b" place="bottom">Becauſe it is as ſoone raiſed as glaſſe is, by thoſe that make it.</note> glaſſe-like choller; &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yels</l>
               <l>With ſuch a foule loud noiſe, that you would ſay</l>
               <l>Surely ſome great <hi>Arcadian</hi> aſſe did bray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt, with much adoe he doth beginne</l>
               <l>To take his booke in hand and ſome faire skinne</l>
               <l>Of ſmooth <note n="c" place="bottom">Yellow on the ſide the haire grew, and white on the other ſide.</note> two-colourd parchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: he takes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Some paper and his knottie reed-like pen.</l>
               <l>Then he complaines how that his inke doth ſtick</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:20"/>In clots at his pens noſe, it is ſo thicke.</l>
               <l>Powre water then to his blacke <note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Sepia</hi> is a ſea-fiſh called a <hi>Cuttell,</hi> whoſe blood the <hi>Romans</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſtead of inke.</note> 
                  <hi>Sepian</hi> iuice,</l>
               <l>He cries, now tis too white. Ha's a device</l>
               <l>For ev'ry thing. So Sometimes he doth plead</l>
               <l>His pen writes double, or his inke doth ſpread.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wretched, vnhappie man! yet growing ſtill</l>
               <l>More wretched! Think'ſt wee're borne to take our fill</l>
               <l>Of ſloth? Why doſt not then like the ſoft Doue</l>
               <l>Or great mens little children, rather loue</l>
               <l>In delicateſt wantonneſſe to lappe</l>
               <l>Some ſoft ſweet ſpoone-meat, as, a little pappe?</l>
               <l>Or angry with the tear, why doſt not crie,</l>
               <l>Refuſing to be ſtilld with Lullabie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">This verſe is an interiected reply of the ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full youth: the next is ſpoken in the perſon of his companion which reprehendeth him.</note> Why can I ſtudie, ſir, with ſuch a quill?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">This verſe is an interiected reply of the ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full youth: the next is ſpoken in the perſon of his companion which reprehendeth him.</note> Alas! whom doſt thou mocke? why pleadſt thou ſtill</l>
               <l>Such vaine ambages? wretched man to flout</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe! Th'art broken! loe, thou leakeſt out!</l>
               <l>And know thou Shalt be Scornd! ſtrike but a pot</l>
               <l>Of ſome raw earth halfe-boild, and will it not</l>
               <l>Tell its owne fault, yeelding a dull crazd ſound?</l>
               <l>Well; <hi>Yet</hi> th'art ſoft moiſt clay, and mayſt be wound</l>
               <l>To any forme: Now therefore, Now make haſt</l>
               <l>To vertue: Preſent time muſt be embrac'd.</l>
               <l>Now like the potters clay, now thou muſt feele</l>
               <l>Sharpe diſciplines effigiating wheele.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">His companions ironicall defence of the others careleſſeneſſe.</note> But, oh, thy father left Thee Land enough,</l>
               <l>And a cleane Salt-ſeller, with houſhold ſtuffe</l>
               <l>Sufficient, needſt Thou then feare any thing?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:20"/>So th' haſt a ſecure pan wherein to bring</l>
               <l>Incenſe to thy protecting <hi>Lares.</hi> Well;</l>
               <l>But think'ſt thou this enough? wilt therefore ſwell,</l>
               <l>And breake thy lungs with an ambitious wind,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that thou thy thouſanth off, doſt find</l>
               <l>Thy branch to be perchance drawne from a tree</l>
               <l>Of ſome high <hi>Thuſcan</hi> true nobilitie?</l>
               <l>Or that becauſe clad in the purple graine</l>
               <l>Meeting <hi>Romes Cenſour</hi> with his pompous traine</l>
               <l>Thou canſt ſalute him, by the name of <hi>Cuzze,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And arrogantly aske him how he does?</l>
               <l>Away: goe pranſe before the multitude</l>
               <l>In theſe thy trappings; ſeeke not to delude</l>
               <l>My iudgement: for I knowe thy ſoule within,</l>
               <l>And ſee thy faults writ in thy outmoſt skinne.</l>
               <l>Art not aſhamd to liue like diſſolute</l>
               <l>Looſe <hi>Natta?</hi> but (alas!) he's deſtitute</l>
               <l>Of Senſe! He ſtands Amaſd in vice! the deepe</l>
               <l>Fat brawne of ſin makes his heart ſoundly ſleepe!</l>
               <l>That now he doth not ſinne! No, he's ſo groſſe,</l>
               <l>So ſtupid, that he's ſenſleſſe of his loſſe!</l>
               <l>And ſunke downe to the depth of vice he'le ſwim</l>
               <l>No more againe vp to the waters brim!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great father of the Gods! when cruell luſt</l>
               <l>Touch'd with inflaming venome, moues th'vniuſt</l>
               <l>Corrupted diſpoſition of fierce kings,</l>
               <l>To act vnworthy and vnkingly things:</l>
               <l>Puniſh them only thus; <hi>Let them but ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faire vertue, and their loſt felicitie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then ſhall their bowels yearne, and they ſhall cry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In ſecret, and wax pale, and pine, and die.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did ever the <hi>Sicilian</hi> braſen bull</l>
               <l>Roare out his torments with a throat more full?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:21"/>Or did the ſword hung by a ſlender thread</l>
               <l>Vp in the golden roofe over the head</l>
               <l>Of the <note n="g" place="margin">Damocles.</note> crownd flatterer, more terrifie</l>
               <l>His ſoule, then when a man ſhall truely cry</l>
               <l>Vnto himſelfe, <hi>I fall, Oh, I doe fall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Downe head-long;</hi> &amp; ſhall Know he's paſt recall?</l>
               <l>And Inwardly grow pale (O wretched life!)</l>
               <l>Which he's afeard to tell his neere deere wife?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Indeed, when I was Young, I like a foole</l>
               <l>Would 'noint my eyes with oile to ſtay from ſchoole:</l>
               <l>When I'de not learne, through ſloath, the ſtately part</l>
               <l>Of dying <hi>Cato,</hi> though 'twere penn'd with art.</l>
               <l>And my too-carefull Maſter prais'd it much:</l>
               <l>And my glad father being moou'd with ſuch</l>
               <l>His praiſes, brought his friends to here his boy</l>
               <l>Brauely act <hi>Cato,</hi> and would ſweat for ioy.</l>
               <l>For then I car'd not to knowe any thing:</l>
               <l>Except how much the luckie Sice would bring:</l>
               <l>Or what the looſing Ace would ſcrape away</l>
               <l>Or that my fellow might not put falſe play</l>
               <l>Vpon me, neatly cogging forth a die</l>
               <l>Out of the ſmall-neck'd <note n="h" place="bottom">They vſed to caſt their dice out of boxes, (as now adaies ſome doe out of ſmall ſaucers) to prevent the ſleight of the hand, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome more cunning gameſters did often practiſe.</note> caſting-box. This I</l>
               <l>Did learne: and for the ſcourge-ſtick I did ſtriue,</l>
               <l>That none his top with greater art might driue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now, Thou art not at This age to learne</l>
               <l>Betweene good and bad manners to diſcerne.</l>
               <l>Noe; thou Haſt learn'd the precepts that are taught</l>
               <l>In the wiſe porch, where curiouſly are wrought</l>
               <l>By <hi>Polygnotus</hi> skill, the conquer'd <hi>Medes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In their ſhort ſloppes: whoſe ſtory overſpreads</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:21"/>The Walls: and where in ſearching hidden truths</l>
               <l>The little-ſleeping cloſe-ſhorne Stoick Youths,</l>
               <l>That feed on huskes and a courſe barly cake,</l>
               <l>Early and late induſtriouſly doe wake.</l>
               <l>And vnto Thee the <note n="i" place="margin">The letter of <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> who by birth was a <hi>Samian.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Samian</hi> letter Y</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſpreading branches teach Philoſophie,</l>
               <l>Hath marked out ev'n as it were with chaulke,</l>
               <l>The high-rear'd right-hand path, wherein to walke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſnort'ſt thou Yet? What? is thy head growne ſlacke?</l>
               <l>Art jaw-falne? Doth their frame begin to cracke?</l>
               <l>Lyeſt yawning, to evaporate th' exceſſe</l>
               <l>Of yeſterdaies oppreſſing drunkenneſſe?</l>
               <l>Haſt thou propos'd thy ſelfe a certaine end?</l>
               <l>And with thy beſt endeavour doſt thou bend</l>
               <l>Thy bow at that? Or, careleſſe of thy hurt,</l>
               <l>Doſt throwe at crowes, with ſtones and clots of durt</l>
               <l>Neglecting where thou runn'ſt? Haſt thou no drift,</l>
               <l>But only for the Preſent how to ſhift?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well, yet be provident; when our ſicke skinne</l>
               <l>Doth with the puffing dropſie once beginne</l>
               <l>To ſwell, 'tis then, thou know'ſt, but vaine to cry</l>
               <l>For <hi>Hellebore;</hi> when a diſeaſe drawes nigh,</l>
               <l>And yet but threatens thee; Then, then prevent</l>
               <l>And meet a danger that is imminent.</l>
               <l>But if thou doſt delay, till't be too late,</l>
               <l>And that thy ſickneſſe once growe deſperate:</l>
               <l>Then would'ſt thou giue <hi>Craterus</hi> halfe thy wealth</l>
               <l>Yet can he not reſtore thee to thy health.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Learne then, O wretched youthes the myſtery</l>
               <l>Of Nature in profound Philoſophy.</l>
               <l>Learne who we are: why we were borne: th' eſtate</l>
               <l>Wherein wee're ſet; And knowe that not by fate</l>
               <l>But wiſdome, we may turne our ſhip with eaſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:22"/>About high-vertues <note n="k" place="margin">An alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mans Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machia.</hi>
                  </note> marke plac'd in the ſeas</l>
               <l>Of this our life. Temperately deſire</l>
               <l>Silver: learne what 'tis lawfull to require</l>
               <l>In prayer: and the perfect vſe, aright,</l>
               <l>Of Money: for which, men ſo ſharply fight:</l>
               <l>What likewiſe to thy Country thou doſt owe,</l>
               <l>And what to thy deare kinſmen; Learne to knowe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whom</hi> 
                  <note n="l" place="bottom">Mee thinkes, theſe lines of mine Author, and eſpecially this word <hi>Deus,</hi> ſeeme to be of that high ſtraine of Divinitie (in a Heathen) which <hi>Plato</hi> reached vnto, when he did profeſſe that hee writte but in ieſt, when he ſaid, <hi>Gods.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>God hath made thee, and in what degree</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſtate of life, he here hath placed thee.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Learne: neither envie thou at the full ſtore</l>
               <l>Of the greas'd Lawyer, though he haue much more</l>
               <l>Proviſion, then his family can ſpend</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt it is ſweet: which the fat <hi>Vmbrians</hi> ſend,</l>
               <l>As gifts to bribe his tongue. Nor grutch to ſee</l>
               <l>His <hi>Marſian</hi> Client bring him for a fee,</l>
               <l>Pepper, gammons of bacon, or ſuch kinde</l>
               <l>Remembrances. Nor let it vex thy minde,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he hath freſh Pilchars to him ſent,</l>
               <l>Before the former barrell be quite ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But heere, me thinks, I heare ſome boiſtrous rough</l>
               <l>Centurion ſay; Tuſh, I haue wit enough</l>
               <l>To ſerue mine owne turne; And Ile never care</l>
               <l>To be <hi>Arceſilas,</hi> or to impaire</l>
               <l>My health, like <hi>Solon:</hi> who doe leane awry</l>
               <l>Their heads, pearcing the earth with a fixt eye:</l>
               <l>When by themſelues they gnaw their murmuring</l>
               <l>And furious ſilence, as 'twere ballancing</l>
               <l>Each word vpon their out-ſtretchd lippe: And when</l>
               <l>They meditate the dreames of old ſicke men,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:22"/>As, <hi>Out of nothing, nothing can be brought:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And that which is, can ne're be turnd to naught.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is it for This they're pale? and that they miſſe</l>
               <l>Their dinner oftentimes, is it for This?</l>
               <l>Why yet they are but ſcorn'd ev'n by the Route,</l>
               <l>The People: and our Luſtie Lads but flout</l>
               <l>Them, and with criſped noſes aloofe off,</l>
               <l>Strongly ingeminate a trembling ſcoffe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Perfius</hi> his anſwere to the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which he makes the Centurion heere vſe.</note> Yet, ſcorne not learning: leſt thy falling ſtate</l>
               <l>Proue ſuch, as this which here I will relate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One ſaid to his Phyſitian, Pray Sir ſee;</l>
               <l>Me thinks I am not as I vſe to be.</l>
               <l>My heart doth quake as if it boaded death:</l>
               <l>And my ſick jaws ſend forth a loathſome breath;</l>
               <l>Pray good Sir feele my Pulſe: and play your part.</l>
               <l>Well, the Phyſitian vs'd his chiefeſt art,</l>
               <l>And bid him reſt Foure daies. But when each vaine</l>
               <l>Began compoſedly to flow againe,</l>
               <l>On the Third night: he bid his ſervant take</l>
               <l>A <note n="n" place="margin">A ſmall flaggon.</note> little thirſting-flaggon, and ſtraight make</l>
               <l>All ſpeed, to the great houſe of ſuch a friend,</l>
               <l>And tell him, he deſir'd him for to ſend</l>
               <l>Some of his milde <hi>Surrentine</hi> wine: and ſo</l>
               <l>Having dranke that, vnto the Baths hee'd go.</l>
               <l>When being there, thither did come by chance</l>
               <l>His owne Phyſitian: who ſtraight caſt a glance</l>
               <l>On this his patient, and to him ſaid,</l>
               <l>Why You are Pale, and are you not afraid?</l>
               <l>Tuſh man, ſaith he, thats Nothing. Yet beware,</l>
               <l>Said his Phyſitian, and pray haue a care,</l>
               <l>What ere this Nothing is. For I doe ſee,</l>
               <l>Your yellow ſickly skinne ſwells ſecretly.</l>
               <l>Well, prethee now, ſaid he, doe not thou raile</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:23"/>At Me: for thou thy ſelfe doſt looke more pale</l>
               <l>And worſe: be not a Tutour vnto Me.</l>
               <l>One I haue had, and buri'd: now for Thee,</l>
               <l>Thou yet remainſt. On then, and doe not ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Said his Phyſitian, and Ile hold my peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This gallant then ſwelling with daintie cheere</l>
               <l>Bathes his pale belly, and without all feare:</l>
               <l>His throat halfe ſtopt with groſſe corrupted fleame,</l>
               <l>Leaſurely breathing a ſulphureous ſteame.</l>
               <l>But midſt his wines a ſuddaine trembling ſeaz'd</l>
               <l>Vpon each ioint of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that his diſeas'd</l>
               <l>Weake hand could not his luke-warme bowle retaine:</l>
               <l>And his vncover'd teeth ev'n gnaſht againe:</l>
               <l>And then through his looſe lips, his fine-oild meate</l>
               <l>He vomits, which he greedily had eate.</l>
               <l>Then were prepared for his funerall</l>
               <l>The <note n="o" place="bottom">At the Funerals of Great Men, they vſed Trumpets: as pipes at the Burials of the meaner ſort.</note> Trumpet, and the Lights: And laſt of all,</l>
               <l>This ſeeming-happy man, that would not doubt,</l>
               <l>His health, being compoſedly laid out</l>
               <l>On his high bed, his biere; and now daub'd o're</l>
               <l>And ev'n bedurted with th'abundant ſtore</l>
               <l>Of ointments; ſtretcheth towr'd the Citie-gate</l>
               <l>His cold dead heeles; &amp; thoſe whoſe beſt eſtate</l>
               <l>But yeſterday, was but to be his ſlaue,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="bottom">It was the cuſtome of the <hi>Romanes</hi> before their deathes to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numitte their ſervants: which was by ſhauing their heads, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a cappe on.</note> Now weare their cappes, and beare him to his graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="bottom">The ſcornefull reply of the Centurion.</note> What? then belike y' apply this ſame to Mee?</l>
               <l>But (wretched foole!) th' art out. For knowe, I'me free.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:23"/>Touch but my veines: feele how my heart doth beate:</l>
               <l>There's but a wonted moderated heate.</l>
               <l>Or feele the bottoms of my feete: or hold</l>
               <l>My hands: thou ſhalt perceaue they are not cold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">The anſwere of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> Tis true. But know ſeduced man; there ſticke</l>
               <l>Diſeaſes in thy Soule; tis That is ſicke.</l>
               <l>For if thou ſee by chance much gold: or ſpie</l>
               <l>Thy neighbours ſmooth-cheek'd wench to caſt an eie</l>
               <l>Vpon thee, ſmiling with a wanton glance:</l>
               <l>Speake true: doth Then thy heart Orderly daunce?</l>
               <l>There's ſet before thee on thy board, to eate,</l>
               <l>In a cold diſh hard hearbes, ſomewhat rough meate;</l>
               <l>And courſe bread ſifted in the people's ſearce:</l>
               <l>Lets trie your chappes. Oh are yee now averſe?</l>
               <l>In thy ſoft mouth there's hid a putrid ſoare,</l>
               <l>Which touch'd with <hi>Common</hi> hearbes, would make thee roare.</l>
               <l>So thy heart's cold, when pale feare doth affright</l>
               <l>Thy haire like eares of corne ſtanding vpright.</l>
               <l>Againe, fierce anger makes thy blood grow hot,</l>
               <l>Ev'n as a fire-brand doth a ſeething pot;</l>
               <l>And then thy flaring eies ſparkling forth fire</l>
               <l>Thou ſai'ſt and doſt So in thy furious ire:</l>
               <l>That mad <hi>Oreſtes</hi> dares ſweare, Such a fact</l>
               <l>None but a man ſtarke mad, ere durſt to act.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="satire">
            <head>THE FOVRTH SATIRE.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>Yong Rulers: The complaint of Luſt</l>
               <l>On Avarice, vnfit though iuſt.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>ARt thou a Common-wealths chiefe Governer?</l>
               <l>(Suppoſe the bearded graue <note n="a" place="margin">Socrates.</note> Philoſopher,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:24"/>Whom the cold draught of Hemlocke forc'd to die,</l>
               <l>Thus to demand) On what doſt thou relie?</l>
               <l>What are thy grounds? ſpeake <hi>Alcibiades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pupill vnto the famous <hi>Pericles.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh, wit and graue diſcretion, I haue heard</l>
               <l>Indeed, do many times Prevent a Beard!</l>
               <l>And ſo Thou knowſt no doubt, though th'art but yong,</l>
               <l>Both when to Speake, and when to hold thy tonge.</l>
               <l>When therefore the vext multitude grow hot</l>
               <l>With choller, and their duty haue forgot:</l>
               <l>Thou doſt but lift vp thy maieſticke hand,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight a gen'rall ſilence doſt command</l>
               <l>Ore the tumultuous rout. Then what doſt ſay?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Theſe three lines are ſpoken in the perſon of this yong Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verner.</note> O yee <hi>Quiritians</hi> (if prevaile I may)</l>
               <l>I thinke This is not juſt that's done by you:</l>
               <l>Nor This: twere better if you Thus did doe.</l>
               <l>For thou canſt weigh truth in the double ſcale</l>
               <l>Of the moſt doubtfull ballance. If it faile,</l>
               <l>Straightwaies Thou know'ſt it: yea, though hid it lie</l>
               <l>Betweene a double crooked falſitie:</l>
               <l>Or if a Rule (ſo perfect is Thy ſight)</l>
               <l>Meaſure not ev'ry thing exactly right.</l>
               <l>And the blacke <note n="c" place="margin">The Iudges being about to giue ſentence of death againſt a man, were wont to write his name in a table, and prefixe before it, the letter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>as</hi> being the firſt of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſignifying hee was to be delivered over to Death.</note> Theta ſigne of deadly ſhame</l>
               <l>Thou can'ſt prefixe 'fore an offenders name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou Canſt doe this. Oh, twere a crime to Doubt.</l>
               <l>Come, come: Thou being faire only without</l>
               <l>And in the skinne, in vaine: leaue off to ſhake</l>
               <l>Thy taile, before the flattring rout, or make</l>
               <l>Suit for great offices, till age and cares</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:24"/>Haue made thee Fit to manage ſuch affaires.</l>
               <l>Thou being fitter yet to drinke good ſtore</l>
               <l>Of pure vnmixt braine-purging <hi>Hellebore.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherein conſiſts thy laſt, thy greateſt wiſh?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">The anſwere of this vaine fellow: and the replie of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> In having ev'ry day a full fat diſh:</l>
               <l>Then with ſweet oile to'noint my skin, and lie</l>
               <l>In the Sunnes pleaſant warmth till it be drie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">The anſwere of this vaine fellow: and the replie of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> Why hadſt thou with the ſelfe ſame queſtion tri'd</l>
               <l>This poore old woman; ſhee had ſo repli'd.</l>
               <l>Goe now and boaſt how thy Nobilitie</l>
               <l>Comes from th' Illuſtrious <hi>Dinomache.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Puffe out thy vaunts, and ſay, I'me comely, faire,</l>
               <l>To graunt thee ſuch Vaine praiſes Ile not care.</l>
               <l>When ragged gran'ame <hi>Baucis,</hi> that does crie</l>
               <l>Vnto the looſer ſervants, <hi>Will yee buie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Any ſweete hearbes,</hi> has as much wit as Thee,</l>
               <l>That thus doſt boaſt of thy vaine pedegree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That no man will deſcend to his Owne heart,</l>
               <l>And ſearch the ſecrets of that hidden part!</l>
               <l>No man! But haue their eies fixt evermore</l>
               <l>Vpon His backe and bagge that goes Before!</l>
               <l>For doe but aske a man, by Chance; D' yee know</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vectidius</hi> farmes? Hee'le ſay, <hi>Vectidius?</hi> Who?</l>
               <l>The Chuffe of <hi>Cures,</hi> he whoſe grounds they ſay</l>
               <l>A kite can ſcarce flie o're in a whole day?</l>
               <l>Him ev'n the Gods oppoſe and the ſure fate</l>
               <l>Of an vnluckie <hi>Genius.</hi> Who (the date</l>
               <l>Of time, bringing againe the Plow-mens <note n="e" place="bottom">Theſe feaſts were called <hi>Compitalia,</hi> and were celebrated in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their <hi>Lares.</hi>
                  </note> feaſt,</l>
               <l>When from their paineful labors they haue ceas'd,</l>
               <l>And now hung vp their weary Oxens yoke</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:25"/>By the worne path vpon ſome aged oke)</l>
               <l>When he ſhould freely laugh, and make good cheere</l>
               <l>For other plow-men (tis but Once a yeere)</l>
               <l>Moſt baſely fearing to pull off the clay</l>
               <l>From his ſmall wine-veſſel; hee'le ſigh, and ſay,</l>
               <l>Pray <hi>Ioue,</hi> that this my Prodigalitie</l>
               <l>Bring me not in the end, to beggerie!</l>
               <l>A coated oignion then with ſalt he eates;</l>
               <l>(His ſervants much applauding ſuch braue meates:</l>
               <l>Nay, and reioycing for their happy lot</l>
               <l>And for the barly-pudding in the pot)</l>
               <l>Then ſparingly he ſuppes in ſteed of beere,</l>
               <l>The cloathy dregges of dying Vineger.</l>
               <l>But ſtraight replies the other, If Thou 'noint'ſt</l>
               <l>With ſupple oile thy foule lubberly ioints</l>
               <l>And ly'ſt in the hot Sunne letting it beate</l>
               <l>Vpon thy skinne, with its ſtrong parching heate:</l>
               <l>There's one whom Thou ſcarce know'ſt, ſtands here hard by,</l>
               <l>Ev'n at thine elbow, that could likewiſe crie</l>
               <l>Againſt Thy manners, and thy lewder art,</l>
               <l>The depilation of thy modeſt part,</l>
               <l>And of thy lunges, to proſtitute thereby</l>
               <l>Vnto a barren luſt thy pathicke thigh.</l>
               <l>Thy Cheekes bearing a kemb'd, oil'd beard: Elſewhere</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="bottom">Reader, in This line, I intendedly depart from the Letter of mine Author, yet without thy loſſe.</note>Why doſt thou too-vniuſtly-ſmooth appeare?</l>
               <l>Scrape on: but though fiue luſtie wraſtlers would</l>
               <l>Roote vp theſe ſpringing plants: yea though they ſhould</l>
               <l>With crooked pinſers, by their tugging oft,</l>
               <l>Weaken thy parts of ſhame, though firſt made ſoft</l>
               <l>With Barbers ſoapie water, ſo to yeeld</l>
               <l>The better, to the plowers of this field:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:25"/>Yet this o're-ſpreading fearne will never bow</l>
               <l>Vnto the deepeſt furrow-making plow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus we wound Others: and doe yeeld agen</l>
               <l>Our thighes vnto the darts of other men.</l>
               <l>And thus we know mans life purſu'd to be</l>
               <l>By this too-much-aſſumed Libertie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="bottom">The paſſage heere, was too-obſcure: wherefore J was forced to be a little diffuſe in the opening of the connection; and ſo inſerted theſe foure verſes.</note> Yet ſome mens faults, becauſe they hidden lie</l>
               <l>From the enquirie of their Enemie,</l>
               <l>Are not obiected to them; yet are knowne</l>
               <l>To him, to whom they crie, We are thine Owne.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt a ſecret wound vnder thy ſide:</l>
               <l>But thy broad gold-boſs'd girdle doth it hide:</l>
               <l>So though thou make Men ſay, Th'art well (in Vaine):</l>
               <l>Will thy Side ſay ſo too, that feeles the paine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou'lt heere perchance reply, What? when as all</l>
               <l>My neighbours Me an ex'lent fellow, call;</l>
               <l>And ſay, I am not as your Common men.</l>
               <l>Shall I, ah, Can I not beleeue 'hem then?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="bottom">The reply of <hi>Perſius</hi> to his owne obiection.</note> Alas, blinde wretch! if at the ſight of gold</l>
               <l>With avaricious loue thou waxeſt cold</l>
               <l>And pale: if ev'ry thing thou likewiſe doe,</l>
               <l>Which griefe-procuring Luſt provokes thee to:</l>
               <l>If on the table of thy Vſurie,</l>
               <l>By moſt oppreſſing heavie crueltie,</l>
               <l>As by a ſtrong deepe-wounding ſcourge, thou make</l>
               <l>Many a ſure-imprinted grievous ſtrake:</l>
               <l>To the falſe-praiſing People thou maiſt lend</l>
               <l>Thy ſpungie, ſucking eares; but to no end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seeme not more then thou art: neither beleeue</l>
               <l>The ignorant applauſe baſe Coblers giue.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:26"/>Liue with thy Selfe, and quickly thou ſhalt ſee,</l>
               <l>The curtal'd ſtore of thy bare povertie.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="satire">
            <head>
               <hi>THE FIFT SATIRE IN FORME</hi> of a Dialogue. <hi>The Speakers.</hi> Perſius, Cornutus.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>Cornutus praiſe: Philoſophie:</l>
               <l>Oppos'd deſires: true Libertie.</l>
            </argument>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <l>OVr Poets vſe to wiſh they had large lunges,</l>
               <l>And a whole hundred voices, mouths, and tongues:</l>
               <l>When they would write a buskin'd Tragedie,</l>
               <l>To be yawn'd out with the ſad Maieſtie</l>
               <l>Of a Tragedian: or deſcribe the high</l>
               <l>Braue-minded <hi>Parthian</hi> pulling from his thigh</l>
               <l>A hooke-like bearded dart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <l>Why ſpeak'ſt Thou thus?</l>
               <l>And heapeſt vp ſuch vaſt robuſtious</l>
               <l>And ſwelling lines, that Thou Thy Selfe doſt need</l>
               <l>A hundred throates, if thou'dſt attaine indeed</l>
               <l>The end which ſuch endeavours tend to? Rather</l>
               <l>Let Them, who'le write ſome Loftie matter, gather</l>
               <l>Clouds off of <hi>Helicon,</hi> to whom the pot</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Progne,</hi> or <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> ſhall grow hot;</l>
               <l>Of which, the fond Tragedian <hi>Glyco</hi> muſt</l>
               <l>Oft make his ſupper. But Thou neither duſt</l>
               <l>Puffe from thy mouthes full bellowes much vaine winde</l>
               <l>The whil'ſt the matters boiling in thy minde,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:26"/>Thy fordge: nor with an inward murmuring</l>
               <l>Hoarſly crow-like caw'ſt out ſome idle thing,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know not what: nor doſt Thou ſtriue to ſtuffe</l>
               <l>Thy ſwelling cheekes, to breake 'hem with a puffe.</l>
               <l>Thy words are words of peace, and accurate</l>
               <l>Thy ſtile; thy mouth not ſwolne, but moderate</l>
               <l>Smooths out thy numbers; Thou canſt touch to th'quicke,</l>
               <l>Pale manners: and with an ingenuous tricke</l>
               <l>Strike a crime Through; And Hence indeed from Crimes</l>
               <l>Doe Thou draw ſtill the ſubiect of Thy rimes;</l>
               <l>And leaue the feaſt made with the feete and head</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Plyſthenes</hi> woefully murthered,</l>
               <l>At ſad <hi>Mycenae:</hi> and doe Thou deſcrie</l>
               <l>The Peoples banquets, full of Luxurie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Surely, I ſtriue not that My leafe may riſe</l>
                  <l>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h ſwelling bubbles of vaine fopperies,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it to giue weight to ſmoake. We ſpeake retir'd:</l>
                  <l>And inwardly I by my Muſe inſpir'd</l>
                  <l>Heere offer ev'n my ſecret heart to bee</l>
                  <l>By Thee tri'd fully. For I'de haue thee ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cornutus,</hi> deareſt friend, how great a part</l>
                  <l>Of my deare, yet divided ſoule Thou art.</l>
                  <l>Knocke on my breaſt: for Thou haſt skill to know</l>
                  <l>What ſoundeth ſolid, and the cover'd ſhew</l>
                  <l>Of a gilt tongue. And oh heere I could craue</l>
                  <l>A hundred voices: that how much I haue</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ixt thee within my many-ſeated breaſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> a pure fluent ſtile might be expreſs'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd that which now ineffable doth dwell</l>
                  <l>Within my heart, in words I heere could tell.</l>
                  <l>When firſt I did begin to leaue to feare</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nder a Maſter: and left off to weare</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y purple-Coate, that ſtill preſerved free</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:27"/>From violation my weake infancie:</l>
                  <l>And when my Golden Boſſe I newly had</l>
                  <l>Hung vp to my <note n="a" place="bottom">To ſignifie their readineſſe and expedition in defence of the houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> which was committed to their tutelary charge.</note> ſuccinct Houſe-Gods: when bad,</l>
                  <l>And ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttering companions guarded mee:</l>
                  <l>When now my White Shield granted Libertie</l>
                  <l>Vnto mine eyes, freely to roue throughout</l>
                  <l>The lewd <hi>Suburra:</hi> when I was in doubt</l>
                  <l>Which way to take: and when my trembling minde</l>
                  <l>Was by pernicious errour almoſt blinde,</l>
                  <l>Miſ-led into divided paths: I then</l>
                  <l>Offer'd my ſelfe to thy Inſtruction. When</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtraightway didſt embrace my tender youth</l>
                  <l>In thy <hi>Socratique</hi> boſome: and the truth</l>
                  <l>Of Thy rule well-appli'd, skilfull to draw</l>
                  <l>Feeble inclining mindes to reaſons law,</l>
                  <l>Shewd me intorted manners: and my mind</l>
                  <l>Was preſs'd by reaſon, thoroughly confin'd</l>
                  <l>To learned precepts, ſtroue to be o'recome;</l>
                  <l>And tooke a Faire forme from Thy skilfull thombe.</l>
                  <l>For I remember oft I with delight</l>
                  <l>Haue ſpent long daies with Thee: and of the Night</l>
                  <l>Haue borrow'd the firſt howres, feaſting with Thee</l>
                  <l>On the choiſe dainties of Philoſophie.</l>
                  <l>One worke we wrought: we reſted both one reſt:</l>
                  <l>Mixing ſevereneſſe, with a Modeſt ieſt.</l>
                  <l>For doubt not, both our birth-daies ioin'd in one</l>
                  <l>Sure league, drawne from one conſtellation:</l>
                  <l>Or the vnchanged <hi>Parca</hi> weigh'd our time</l>
                  <l>With an ev'n ballance: or that firſt, that prime</l>
                  <l>Birth-howre of vs true friends did bleſſedly</l>
                  <l>Place our embracing fates in <hi>Gemini:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:27"/>And heavie <hi>Saturnes</hi> ſterne malignitie</l>
                  <l>Was broke by our good <hi>Ioues</hi> benignitie.</l>
                  <l>I knowe not What, but ſure Some Starre I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Which inwardly diſpoſes me towrds Thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet there's a thouſand ſorts of men: and ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Varietie doth humane actions change.</l>
                  <l>Each hath his ſev'rall will: nor doe All liue</l>
                  <l>With One deſire, For, One his minde doth giue</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Merchandizing,</hi> and with care doth runne</l>
                  <l>Out to the Eaſt vnder the riſing Sunne,</l>
                  <l>To get rough pepper, and pale Cummin ſeed</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Romane</hi> wares Another loues to feed</l>
                  <l>His panch, and then ſwell with deſtilling ſleepe;</l>
                  <l>A third doth <hi>Mars</hi>-field wraſtlings duely keepe;</l>
                  <l>A fourth turnes banke-rupt by the deſp'rate die;</l>
                  <l>A fift growes rotten by damn'd Venerie.</l>
                  <l>But when the knottie hand-gout has once broke</l>
                  <l>Their ioynts, as th'boughes of ſome decayed oke:</l>
                  <l>Anger and griefe doe then begin a ſtrife</l>
                  <l>Within them, for their baſe and durtie life</l>
                  <l>Now ſpent: when now, but now too late, they looke</l>
                  <l>Vpon the life they wretchedly forſooke.</l>
                  <l>But Thou in learned writings doſt by night</l>
                  <l>Grow pale. Thou makeſt it thy chiefe delight</l>
                  <l>To ſow yong purged eares with fruitfull truths,</l>
                  <l>With good <hi>Cleanthes</hi> fruit. Draw Hence yee youths,</l>
                  <l>Yee old men, for your ſelues, ſome Certaine end:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome helpes from cares your old age to defend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To Morrow wee'le doe this. <note n="b" place="bottom">He brings them in anſwering for themſelues and then be replies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ine vnto them.</note> Alas! you'le doe</l>
                  <l>The ſame, to-morrow. 'Why aske we of you</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o much, to wit, only One Day? <note n="c" place="bottom">Another anſwere of theirs, with his owne reply.</note> But when</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:28"/>The Third day comes, we haue conſumed then</l>
                  <l>To-Morrow Yeſterday: and thus to borrow</l>
                  <l>Of time, though yet to come, ſtill one To-morrow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will ſecretly driue out our Yeares at laſt,</l>
                  <l>When Ev'ry day a New day will be paſt,</l>
                  <l>Never to be recover'd. For Thou Wheele</l>
                  <l>Which doſt about the Second Axle reele</l>
                  <l>Hindermoſt, maiſt in vaine ſtriue to o'retake</l>
                  <l>The Firſt ſtill turning forward, which doth make</l>
                  <l>Like haſt, with equall ſwiftnes: though thou bee</l>
                  <l>Hard by it plac'd vnder the ſelfe-ſame tree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whos'ever then True Libertie would gaine,</l>
                  <l>Let him embrace Philoſophie: for vaine</l>
                  <l>Is Other freedome; Such, to wit, whereby</l>
                  <l>Any new <hi>Publius</hi> may familiarly</l>
                  <l>In his (the <hi>Veline</hi>) tribe courſe corne demand</l>
                  <l>By bringing but his Token in his hand.</l>
                  <l>O men barraine of truth, that thinke they can</l>
                  <l>Make, with a Turning, a <hi>Quiritian!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Heer's <hi>Dama</hi> a baſe horſe-keeper not worth</l>
                  <l>Three halfe-pence, a meere ſot, that can't looke forth</l>
                  <l>From out the miſt of <hi>Jgnorance,</hi> and one</l>
                  <l>Who'le lie ev'n for the leaſt occaſion,</l>
                  <l>For horſe-bread; whom if 's Maſter turne about,</l>
                  <l>I' th' moment of the Whirling he goes out</l>
                  <l>Straight, <hi>Marcus Dama.</hi> The Gods! Darſt denie</l>
                  <l>To truſt one, <hi>Marcus</hi> being ſuretie?</l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>Marcus</hi> being iudge, art pale with feare</l>
                  <l>Of Wrong? <hi>Marcus</hi> ſaid it: then thou mayſt ſweare</l>
                  <l>Tis true. Now <hi>Marcus</hi> ſeale the Bond. Oh, heer's</l>
                  <l>Braue Libertie and true, which our Cap weares</l>
                  <l>As well as Wee! <note n="d" place="bottom">The anſwere of <hi>Dama</hi> now Manumiſs'd.</note> Why is there any free,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:28"/>But he, the which doth liue at Libertie?</l>
                  <l>I liue at libertie, and am not I</l>
                  <l>More free then <hi>Brutus</hi> then? <note n="e" place="bottom">The reply of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                     </note> Oh heere ſtands by</l>
                  <l>A well-taught <hi>Stoick,</hi> whoſe more purged eare</l>
                  <l>Is waſh'd, as 'twere, with Truths ſharpe vineger,</l>
                  <l>That ſayes, I grant the Firſt; but where you ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>J liue at Libertie,</hi> take That away.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="bottom">Another anſwere of <hi>Dama.</hi>
                     </note> Why? ſince I came from th' <hi>Praetors</hi> rod Mine Owne</l>
                  <l>Free man, Ile Now be ſubiect vnto none;</l>
                  <l>And why may n't I doe with full liberty</l>
                  <l>Whats'e're <note n="g" place="bottom">A fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Lawyer, and afterwards a Knight of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Maſurius</hi> doth not deny?</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="bottom">Another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                     </note> Oh, learne: but this thine anger firſt depoſe,</l>
                  <l>And let fall from thy too-much-wrinkled noſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy rugged ſcoffe? whilſt from thy lunges I pull</l>
                  <l>Theſe old wiues tales, of which thy breaſt's Yet full.</l>
                  <l>It was not in the <hi>Praetors</hi> pow'r to giue</l>
                  <l>Pure Wiſdome vnto Fooles, or make Them liue</l>
                  <l>By Reaſons rule. No; thou ſhalt ſooner fit</l>
                  <l>Vnto the harpe, a rough rude ſouldiers wit.</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt which Reaſon doth ſtand, and ſecretly</l>
                  <l>Whiſpers him in the eare, and ſayes, Fie, Fie:</l>
                  <l>Never attempt what thou canſt nere reach to,</l>
                  <l>And only ſpoile, whilſt thou doſt ſtriue to do.</l>
                  <l>The law of man and nature both deny</l>
                  <l>Weake Ignorance the priviledge to trie</l>
                  <l>Forbidden things. Doſt Thou mixe <hi>Hellebore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For a ſicke patient, who ne're tri'd'ſt before</l>
                  <l>To weigh 't exactly to a Dramme? The art</l>
                  <l>Of Phyſicke bids thee not-dare act This part.</l>
                  <l>If a rude high-ſhooed clowne offer to ſteere</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:29"/>A ſhippe, not knowing his guide <hi>Lucifer:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Sea-God <hi>Melicerta</hi> may exclame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The brow of modeſtie has loſt all ſhame?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Has vertues art taught thee to walke vpright?</l>
                  <l>And canſt thou with a perſpicacious ſight</l>
                  <l>Diſcerne the Shew of Truth from truth? Doſt know</l>
                  <l>Counterfaite gold by th'Sound? and canſt thou ſhew</l>
                  <l>What things to follow, what things to decline,</l>
                  <l>The firſt with Chaulke, the laſt with Coale to ſigne?</l>
                  <l>Art of confin'd deſires? haſt thou a ſmall</l>
                  <l>And pretty well-trimm'd houſe? art kinde to all</l>
                  <l>Thy friends? canſt wiſely ſometimes Shut thy ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes Open thy garners to the poore,</l>
                  <l>And with a pure affection vnhurt</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou paſſe over money <note n="i" place="bottom">An alluſion to the ſport that children vſed: who tying a peece of money to the end of a ſtring, would cover the ſtring with durt and let the money bee ſeene, which, when any greedie fellow paſſing by, would ſtoope to take vp, they would plucke-in the ſtring; and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude him.</note> fixt i'th durt?</l>
                  <l>Nor, as a greedy glutton, loue to licke</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mercuriall</hi> ſpittle, which doth vſe to ſticke</l>
                  <l>Vpon the lippes of Niggards? When as all</l>
                  <l>Theſe things thou mayſt thine owne moſt truely call;</l>
                  <l>Then, Oh be wiſe, enioy true Libertie,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Praetors,</hi> yea, and great <hi>Joue</hi> bleſſing thee.</l>
                  <l>But Thou but th'other day of Our degree,</l>
                  <l>Retaining ſtill thy Old skinne, being free</l>
                  <l>Only in a ſmooth brow, that outward part,</l>
                  <l>Deepe ſubtilty lurking in thy foule heart:</l>
                  <l>The Liberty I gaue thee, I againe</l>
                  <l>Recall, and doe tie Shorter Now thy chaine.</l>
                  <l>For Reaſon vnto Thee doth Nothing lend:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:29"/>Lift but thy <note n="k" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Ramirez</hi> (in his Commentary on <hi>Martial:</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epig. <hi>1.</hi>) would perſwade vs that this place is meant <hi>de Medio digito,</hi> but his expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſomewhat ranke, and J will iuſtly oppoſe him with that diſcreet admonition of <hi>Turnebus</hi> (Adverſ. lib. <hi>23.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>) <hi>Non ſunt tam ex alto ducendi ſenſus, de quibus poeta nihil cogitârit.</hi>
                     </note> Finger vp, thou doſt offend;</l>
                  <l>And what's ſo ſmall? But, thou ſhalt nere obtaine</l>
                  <l>By any francke-incenſe, that the Leaſt Graine</l>
                  <l>Of wiſdome ſhall ere reſt within a foole:</l>
                  <l>To mix Theſe Two, is againſt Natures rule.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhalt thou, thou remaining a Clowne ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Ere daunce three meaſures with <hi>Bathyllus</hi> skill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>'me Free.<note n="l" place="bottom">An other reply of Dama, and the anſwere of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                     </note> How canſt thou ſay ſo, thy affection</l>
                  <l>Being in vaſſal'd to the worſt ſubiection?</l>
                  <l>Knowſt thou no other Maſter, but he whom</l>
                  <l>The Manumitting rod did free thee from?</l>
                  <l>Indeed if Now, one ſay imperiouſly</l>
                  <l>To 's ſlaue; Goe, Sirra, carry preſently</l>
                  <l>This linnen to <hi>Criſpinus</hi> Bathes; doſt ſtand</l>
                  <l>Still, Lazie knaue? This his ſevere command</l>
                  <l>Doth moue thee nothing: becauſe now no whip</l>
                  <l>May ſcourge Thy Lazie ſides, to make Thee skip.</l>
                  <l>But if within, in thy ſicke lungs doe ſpring</l>
                  <l>Head-ſtrong deſires, art Thou in any thing</l>
                  <l>Leſſe ſervile then, then is ſuch a poore knaue,</l>
                  <l>Whom th' whip &amp; feare of's Maſter made a ſlaue?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou lying long in bed, avarice cries,</l>
                  <l>Vp, vp, Not yet, ſaiſt thou: For ſhame ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Cries ſhe; I can't, thou do'ſt reply: Why ſo,</l>
                  <l>Saies ſhee againe? Riſe, Riſe; doſt thou not knowe</l>
                  <l>What thou ſhouldſt doe? Why goe to th' Sea, bring thence</l>
                  <l>Fiſh, Beaver-oile, flaxe, Eben, franckincenſe,</l>
                  <l>And looſning wines of <hi>Co;</hi> and be the firſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:30"/>To fetch from th' Camel, whilſt he yet doth thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Freſh pepper: exchange ſomewhat, and forſweare</l>
                  <l>For Gaine. O but (alas!) then <hi>Ioue</hi> will heare</l>
                  <l>Why, foole, if thou wilt dwell with <hi>Joue,</hi> thou ſhalt</l>
                  <l>Striving but to get out one taſt of ſalt,</l>
                  <l>Boare a hoale through thy oft-lick'd ſalt-ſeller.</l>
                  <l>Well; being got vp, thou doſt (not to deferre</l>
                  <l>To execute her will) provide thy men</l>
                  <l>Bagges for to lay their cloathes in, and then</l>
                  <l>Lai'ſt-in wine, with ſuch other things thou knowſt</l>
                  <l>Are fit for Navigation: then ſtraight go'ſt</l>
                  <l>To ſhippe; where nothing hinders thee to ſaile</l>
                  <l>O're the <hi>Aegaean</hi> Sea with a full gaile,</l>
                  <l>But Luxurie. That doth ſeduce thy weake</l>
                  <l>Vnſtayedneſſe, and thus with art doth ſpeake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whether, Oh whether madman, doſt thou run?</l>
                  <l>Whether? What lackſt thou? What wouldſt thou haue done?</l>
                  <l>(<note n="m" place="bottom">Theſe two lines, the Poet interiects in his owne perſon.</note> And now thy hot breaſt with ſtrong ire doth ſwell,</l>
                  <l>Which a whole pot of Hemlock can ſcarce quell.)</l>
                  <l>Wilt Thou paſſe ore the Seas? Wilt Thou ere eate</l>
                  <l>Thy Supper, making a Stretch'd Rope thy ſeate?</l>
                  <l>Shall a broad-bottom'd tankard that does ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke</l>
                  <l>Of pitch, fume out the wine, that Thou muſt drinke?</l>
                  <l>Nay, vile ruddie <hi>Veientane</hi> wine? ſtriv'ſt thou</l>
                  <l>To make thy lab'ring money ſweat forth now</l>
                  <l>Eleav'n in twelue, the which did Heere obtaine</l>
                  <l>Ne're aboue Fiue in Twelue, a modeſt gaine?</l>
                  <l>Come, come: cheriſh thy <hi>Genius:</hi> let's be free</l>
                  <l>T' enioy a full delight: for without Me</l>
                  <l>Life is Not: and remember that ere long.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be but a Ghoſt, duſt, and the ſong</l>
                  <l>O' th' People. Thinke how thou by death ſhalt paſſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:30"/>Away, like Time. This which I'ue Spoke, It was.</l>
                  <l>What doſt thou now? Two hookes a double way</l>
                  <l>Now drawe thee; Wilt thou this, or I his obey?</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt be ſlaue to both alternately:</l>
                  <l>Now ſerving Avarice, now Luxurie.</l>
                  <l>Nor maiſt thou, if thou doſt for Once withſtand</l>
                  <l>Their inſtant and importunate command,</l>
                  <l>Say ſtraight, I'ue broake their bands; For, loe,</l>
                  <l>A dogge by tugging breakes his knot, juſt ſo,</l>
                  <l>Who, though he runne away and bite and ſtraine,</l>
                  <l>Yet at his necke doth traile much of his chaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chaereſtratus</hi> in ſerious meditation</l>
                  <l>Biting his naile to th' quicke through deepe vexation</l>
                  <l>Saies to his man; <hi>Davus,</hi> I now intend</l>
                  <l>All my fore-paſſed greefes and Loue to end;</l>
                  <l>Beleeue me. For ſhall I bee ſtill a ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Vnto my ſober carefull friends good name?</l>
                  <l>Shall I ſpend all my ſtocke with infamie</l>
                  <l>At the lewd threſhold of a Stews? Shall I</l>
                  <l>Drunke before <hi>Chryſis</hi> 'nointed moiſt doores ſtand</l>
                  <l>Singing, my torch extinguiſh'd in my hand?</l>
                  <l>O <note n="n" place="margin">
                        <hi>Davus</hi> his reioycing at his Maſters promiſed reformation.</note> rare yong <hi>Master!</hi> Be hence-forward wiſe:</l>
                  <l>And offer vp a lambe in ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>To thy protecting Gods. <note n="o" place="margin">The interrogation of <hi>Chaereſtratus</hi> to his ſervant <hi>Davus.</hi>
                     </note> But doſt beleeue</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Davus,</hi> if I forſake her, that ſheele grieue?</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Davus</hi> his indignation, at his Maſters weake inconſtancie.</note> Doſt trifle, Idle boy? Then ſhe ſhall breake</l>
                  <l>Thy pate with her red pantofle, and wreake</l>
                  <l>Her ſpight vpon thee, that thou ſhalt not dare</l>
                  <l>To quake, nor bite her faſt-entangling ſnare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:31"/>Th'art Now averſe and violent; but when</l>
                  <l>She ſhall perchance but call thee: thou'lt ſay then,</l>
                  <l>I come ſtraightwaies; for, why? what ſhould I doe?</l>
                  <l>Sha'n't I goe to my Loue, when Shee doth Wooe,</l>
                  <l>And Sends for me? But if thou canſt Now, Now</l>
                  <l>Redeeme thy ſelfe All and Entire; Thou, Thou</l>
                  <l>Art that thriſe-happy man, that only He</l>
                  <l>Whom Only, We iudge to be Truely free.</l>
                  <l>Not he, o're whom the fooliſh <hi>Lictor</hi> wagges</l>
                  <l>His rod, and of him, as His Freeman bragges.</l>
                  <l>For, Oh, can he be truely call'd his owne</l>
                  <l>Whom Candidate Chaulkie Ambition</l>
                  <l>Drawes gaping to Her lure? To whom ſhe cries,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="bottom">The words of Ambition.</note>Vnto thy Clients ſalutations riſe</l>
                  <l>By time, and giue a lib'rall doale of peaſe</l>
                  <l>Vnto the ſcrambling multitude: that theſe</l>
                  <l>Our large <hi>Floralia</hi> may be made the talke</l>
                  <l>Of Aged men hereafter as they walke</l>
                  <l>In the warme Sun; For what can be More braue?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="bottom">Theſe words are ſpoken in the perſon of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                     </note>And art not Superſtitious to haue</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Herods</hi> birth-day, many candles plac'd</l>
                  <l>In order i'th' oild window, much defac'd</l>
                  <l>By the fat clowd the which they vomit out,</l>
                  <l>Though with ſweet violets th'are deck'd about;</l>
                  <l>And t'haue a Tunies taile, as 'twe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to ſwimme</l>
                  <l>In a red diſh, thy white bowle full to th' brimme</l>
                  <l>With wine, yet doſt nor faſt till night, and pray</l>
                  <l>All the <hi>Iewes</hi> circumciſed Saboth-day?</l>
                  <l>Then with Hobgoblins, and the feigned feare</l>
                  <l>Of danger from a crackt egge, and th' auſtere</l>
                  <l>Graue Prieſts of <hi>Cybell,</hi> and the one-eied maide</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20884:31"/>Of <hi>Iſis</hi> with her timbrell, th'art diſmaid.</l>
                  <l>And thinkſt the Gods will puffe with ſome diſeaſe</l>
                  <l>Thy ſwelling skinne: if thou ſhalt them diſpleaſe:</l>
                  <l>Refuſing by their graue rules to be led,</l>
                  <l>To taſt each morne three times a Garlicke-head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſaieſt thou yet, thou liu'ſt at libertie,</l>
                  <l>Being ſubiect to th' extreameſt vanitie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſpeake this, which the Gods doe knowe, is true,</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt full-veind Souldiers: what would ſtraight enſue?</l>
                  <l>Some vaſt <hi>Volpenius</hi> with a full deepe throate</l>
                  <l>Would bellow out a laugh, in a baſe note:</l>
                  <l>And ten times ten Philoſophers of <hi>Greece</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would ſcarcely prize at a clipt Ten-groates peece.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="satire">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:32"/>
            <head>THE SIXT AND LAST SATIRE TO his friend <hi>Caeſius Baſſus</hi> a Lyrique Poët.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Argument.</head>
               <l>The pining Niggards fruitleſſe care,</l>
               <l>To feed the luſt of his lewd heire.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw, <hi>Baſſus</hi> hath the cold made thee retire</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe, this winter, to the <hi>Sabine</hi> fire?</l>
               <l>Doe thy old harpe and ſtrings liue to thee ſtill,</l>
               <l>Sounding lowd muſicke with a ſtiffer quill?</l>
               <l>Great workman! whoſe bleſt Muſe ſweet lines affordes,</l>
               <l>Full of the Natiue beauty of Old words:</l>
               <l>And on the <hi>Romane</hi> harpe with happyneſſe</l>
               <l>Of skill, a maſculine, ſtrong ſound t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expreſſe:</l>
               <l>Now playing yong mens ſports, now playing ſome</l>
               <l>Braue Old mens actions, with an honeſt thombe.</l>
               <l>The warme <hi>Ligurian</hi> ſhoare growes hot to Mee:</l>
               <l>And I'me now winterd at my Natiue Sea;</l>
               <l>Where the rocks yeeld a ſhoare to them that ſaile</l>
               <l>And where the haven into a large vale</l>
               <l>Retires it ſelfe. <hi>Tis fairely worth the ſight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The port of Luna, full of much delight.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus ſaid wiſe <hi>Ennius</hi> Aft'r h' had dreamd he was</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Homer,</hi> the fift form'd by <hi>Pythagoras</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Peacockes ſoule. Here I retir'd liue free</l>
               <l>From caring what the People thinke of me:</l>
               <l>And what th' vnluckie South-wind doth prepare</l>
               <l>For cattle; Nor doe I take greefe or care</l>
               <l>If that my neighbours field's more fat then mine.</l>
               <l>Let all poore-borne grow rich, Ile never pine</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:32"/>With ſtooping age, for That: or want good cheere:</l>
               <l>Or touch the ſigne of dreggy ſealed beere</l>
               <l>In a hoar'd flaggon. Yet another may</l>
               <l>Diſſent from this. For oft the ſame birth-day</l>
               <l>Hath an Aſcendent ſtrongly influent</l>
               <l>Producing ev'n in twinnes a different</l>
               <l>Yea an oppoſed <hi>Genius.</hi> For the one</l>
               <l>Warily with great circumſpection,</l>
               <l>And on his Birth-day only, dips his drie</l>
               <l>Courſe hearbs in briniſh ſauce, which he doth buy</l>
               <l>In a ſmall cup, His Owne ſelfe Sprinkeling</l>
               <l>His diſh with Pepper as a Holy thing.</l>
               <l>The other a braue boy couragiouſly</l>
               <l>Spends his large portion in luxurie</l>
               <l>On his conſuming tooth. But as for Mine,</l>
               <l>Ile Vſe it: yet nere let my Freedmen dine</l>
               <l>With Turbets: nor be curious-mouth'd to know</l>
               <l>But by the taſt if 't be a Thruſh or noe.</l>
               <l>Proportion thy expences by thy gaine:</l>
               <l>And grind out freely (for thou maiſt) thy graine</l>
               <l>Laid vp within thy barnes. What ſhouldſt thou feare?</l>
               <l>But harrow, and behold ſtraight will appeare</l>
               <l>Another harveſt. <note n="a" place="margin">The covetous mans pretended reaſon in defence of himſelfe.</note> Why, I Would thus ſpend,</l>
               <l>But Dutie hinders me. For my poore friend,</l>
               <l>His ſhippe being ſplit, held by the <hi>Brutian</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sharpe rockes; and buri'd in th' <hi>Jonian</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rough waues all his eſtate, and his deafe cries</l>
               <l>Neglected by the Gods: and himſelfe lies</l>
               <l>Vpon the ſhoare with his great Gods, which he</l>
               <l>Caught from his broken ſhip, whoſe ribs now be</l>
               <l>Expos'd vnto the Cormorant. <note n="b" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> his replie.</note> Nay, Now</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:33"/>Giue him ſome of thy Land: and doe not thou</l>
               <l>Thinke thou canſt be Too free; Let him not lacke,</l>
               <l>Wandring with a Greene <note n="*" place="margin">The table of his ſhipwrack</note> Table at his backe.</l>
               <l>But if thou' impaire thy wealth, thy angred heire</l>
               <l>Of thy laſt funerall-feaſt will take ſmall care:</l>
               <l>And with neglect into thy vrne will throw</l>
               <l>Thy bones without perfumes, careleſſe to know</l>
               <l>Whether he buy dull-ſmelling Cinnamum,</l>
               <l>Or Caſia corrupt with Cherry-gumme.</l>
               <l>Hee'le ſay. What doſt thou idly ſpend thy wealth.</l>
               <l>My portion, being in thy perfect Health?</l>
               <l>But more; I'me ſure there's thriftie <hi>Beſtius</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth preſſe your learnedſt <hi>Graecian</hi> Doctors, thus;</l>
               <l>Thus 'tis, ſince your Fond Liberalitie,</l>
               <l>Rather <note n="c" place="bottom">Thus with the moſt accurate Interpreters, J render <hi>Maris Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> taking <hi>Maris</hi> for the genitiue caſe of <hi>Mas,</hi> not of <hi>Mare;</hi> For then there were a manifeſt contradiction in the ſenſe; becauſe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, he ſayes, it came from <hi>Greece,</hi> and ſo by conſequent, over the <hi>Sea.</hi>
                  </note> emaſculate ſoft Luxurie,</l>
               <l>With pepper, dates, and other ware hath come</l>
               <l>From your lewd <hi>Greece</hi> vnto our Citie <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our very Mowers doe with too much oile</l>
               <l>Their ancient wholeſome meate Sawcily ſpoile.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Perſius</hi> heere anſweres to the obiection, which hee himſelfe brought for the covetous man.</note>But fearſt theſe things beyond thy Graue-Draw neere,</l>
               <l>Thou whoſoere ſhalt be My heire, and heare:</l>
               <l>And that into our talke none may intrude,</l>
               <l>Let vs retire from the thicke multitude.</l>
               <l>My friend, know'ſt not the newes? <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath ſent</l>
               <l>A Laurell for a ſigne and ornament</l>
               <l>Of his great conqueſt over <hi>Germanie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the cold aſhes which before did lie</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:33"/>Vpon the Altars, are now ſwept away:</l>
               <l>And with great care and ioy <note n="e" place="bottom">The Emperour <hi>Caligula's</hi> wife makes all things ready for the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</note> 
                  <hi>Caeſonia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fixeth the conquer'd Kings armour of proofe</l>
               <l>And all their weapons to the temples roofe:</l>
               <l>Clads all the captiues in a durt-browne freiſe:</l>
               <l>Placeth the <hi>Rheni</hi> of a huge vaſt ſize:</l>
               <l>And orders all their coaches: Wherefore I</l>
               <l>Will bring for this ſo happy victory</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="bottom">The <hi>Romans</hi> counted their Fencers-ſhewes and Plaies a part of their Religion; as <hi>Turnebus</hi> well obſerues, in his <hi>Adverſ. lib. 39. cap. 7. p. 1093.</hi>
                  </note>To th' Gods and our great Captaines <hi>Genius</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A hundred paire of fencers. I being thus</l>
               <l>Freely diſpos'd, who doth forbid? Dar'ſt Thou?</l>
               <l>Woe, if thou yeeld'ſt not. Say, that I'me pleas'd now</l>
               <l>Vpon the people to beſtow a doale</l>
               <l>Of oile and fleſh-pies: doſt thou dare controule?</l>
               <l>Speake out, and plainely. Why, your land, thou'lt ſay,</l>
               <l>Is not ſo fat, ſo boneleſſe, but I may,</l>
               <l>For any cauſe I ſee, not greatly care,</l>
               <l>Whether or noe, you doe make Me your Heire.</l>
               <l>Well then, ſcorne Thou my Loue; yet thus much knowe:</l>
               <l>Enow will be my heire, and thanke me too.</l>
               <l>For were none of my fathers ſiſters left:</l>
               <l>No couſen-germane: or were I bereft</l>
               <l>Of all my vnkle's neece's daughters: ſay,</l>
               <l>My mothers ſiſter had di'd barraine: nay,</l>
               <l>That none ſprung from my grandame did ſurviue:</l>
               <l>Briefely, that not one kinſman were aliue:</l>
               <l>Ile goe but to <note n="g" place="bottom">Theſe were places not farre from <hi>Rome,</hi> where beggers vſed to aske almes of paſſengers.</note>
                  <hi>Bovillae,</hi> or the <note n="g" place="margin">Theſe were places not farre from <hi>Rome,</hi> where beggers vſed to aske almes of paſſengers.</note> hill</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Virbius,</hi> where ſtandeth ready ſtill,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:34"/>Poore <hi>Mannius:</hi> He ſhall be my heire. <note n="h" place="bottom">The interrogation of his covetous heire, and the reply of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> What Hee?</l>
               <l>A ſonne o' th' Earth? Obſcure? <note n="h" place="bottom">The interrogation of his covetous heire, and the reply of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> Why aske of Me,</l>
               <l>Who was my fourth Forefather, I can't Well</l>
               <l>And Readily declare; though I Can tell.</l>
               <l>But if you 'de knowe His father, and againe</l>
               <l>That fathers father: ſure you muſt remaine</l>
               <l>Satisfied thus; That He did drawe His birth</l>
               <l>Immediatly from his mother earth;</l>
               <l>And ſo at laſt, you'le finde <hi>Mannius</hi> to be</l>
               <l>By right of kinne, great vnkle vnto Me.</l>
               <l>Yet why at all ſhould'ſt Thou indeed deſire</l>
               <l>To be my Heire, when thou might'ſt be my Sire</l>
               <l>For Age? and why ſhould'ſt thou demand of Mee</l>
               <l>My torch, when I in <note n="i" place="bottom">An alluſion to the race celebrated in honour of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> where the firſt running with a torch in his hand, when he was wearie, gaue it to the next after him.</note> courſe runne After Thee?</l>
               <l>Yet if thou be my heire, me thinkes, thou oughtſt</l>
               <l>To be content, with what thou never bought'ſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>I'me <hi>Mercurie,</hi> and come, to Thee, a God,</l>
               <l>As he is <note n="k" place="bottom">With a purſe of money in his hand.</note> Painted. With a churliſh nod</l>
               <l>Scorn'ſt my free offer? Wilt not thou be glad</l>
               <l>For what is left? <note n="l" place="bottom">The murmuring obiection of his covetous heire, and the reply of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> Why, heeres not all You had</l>
               <l>Left to You by Your father. <note n="l" place="bottom">The murmuring obiection of his covetous heire, and the reply of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> True indeed.</l>
               <l>Much I did ſpend on mine owne proper need.</l>
               <l>But, briefly, this is all is left: which All</l>
               <l>I'le Giue to thee; And doe not thou now brawle</l>
               <l>Vnkindly with me: neither aske me where</l>
               <l>Is that which <hi>Tadius</hi> left me: and ne're</l>
               <l>Giue me hard words, as fathers drawing nigh</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:34"/>Their end, doe giue their ſonnes before they die;</l>
               <l>Saying, See thou put out the Principall:</l>
               <l>And ſpend but of the Vſe: let That be all.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="bottom">One murmuring interrogation more, of his greedy heire; and the reply of <hi>Perſius</hi> full of indignation.</note> But yet, What's Left? <note n="m" place="bottom">One murmuring interrogation more, of his greedy heire; and the reply of <hi>Perſius</hi> full of indignation.</note> What's left? Now lib'rally</l>
               <l>Pow're boy, pow're oile vpon my hearbes. Shall I</l>
               <l>Vpon a high feſtivall day, be fed</l>
               <l>With a ſod nettle, and a leane ſwines head</l>
               <l>Hung vp i'th'ſmoake by th'eare; vnto the end</l>
               <l>This lewd knaue may My goods hereafter ſpend?</l>
               <l>And fill'd with dainty jiblets, without ſhame</l>
               <l>Lewdly embrace a ſoft <hi>Patrician</hi> Dame;</l>
               <l>When as his wayward, full-ſwolne, chiding veine;</l>
               <l>With an vncertaine luſt doth ſob againe?</l>
               <l>Shall I be like the warpe of bare cloath, that</l>
               <l>To him a ſtrutting panch may quagge with fat?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="bottom">A ſatiricall Irony in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome Third Speaker.</note> Oh, ſell thy Soule for Gaine, to leaue thy heire</l>
               <l>Wealthy: and ſo thou getteſt by thy ware,</l>
               <l>Ne're care how honeſtly. Sift ev'ry coaſt</l>
               <l>Of the whole world, that thou mayſt truely boaſt,</l>
               <l>No man feedes fatter <hi>Cappadocian</hi> knaues</l>
               <l>In a rough cage, then are Thy luſtie ſlaues.</l>
               <l>Double thy wealth. <note n="o" place="bottom">The anſwere of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
                  </note> Tis done; nay't has increas'd</l>
               <l>Three, foure, ten-fold as much. Yet ſcarce is ceas'd</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now, where likewiſe I may reſt, deſigne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> thou that didſt Thy <note n="p" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Sorites,</hi> of which kinde of Argumentation, <hi>Chryſippus</hi> was the Authour.</note> heape confine.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>THE END OF PERSIVS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translators_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:20884:35"/>
            <head>AN APOSTROPHE OF THE TRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatour to his Authour <hi>Perſius.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THou art Redeem'd; Nor has the Fate of Time</l>
               <l>And Vice ſeiz'd on thy glory. The Worſt crime</l>
               <l>Which does o'recloud the Guilty, addes to Thee</l>
               <l>A Luſtre, which out ſhines obſcurity.</l>
               <l>Who thought not, that the Great-borne Spirit of <hi>Rome</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had lien o'rewhelm'd in her Last <hi>Brutus</hi> tombe?</l>
               <l>Yet did it Not: but did at laſt bring forth</l>
               <l>Thee, the Example of her Ancient worth.</l>
               <l>Jn whom, had <hi>Veſta's</hi> fire by which <hi>Rome</hi> Stood</l>
               <l>Beene out, there might haue yet beene found as good.</l>
               <l>Mount then, thou purer fire, and let thy heate</l>
               <l>Strongly exhale from their infectious ſeate</l>
               <l>Th' envenom'd fogges of vice; And then inflame</l>
               <l>Them, that they may be lights to their Owne ſhame;</l>
               <l>Which, as a Comet, may affright the earth</l>
               <l>With horror, at its owne prodigious birth;</l>
               <l>And, with its darting taile threatning dread</l>
               <l>Vengeance, point-out to wrath each guilty head.</l>
               <l>Bee thou the <hi>Veſtall</hi> fire, thy Prieſt Ile bee,</l>
               <l>And conſecrate my vigilance to Thee.</l>
               <l>Bee thou th' enlifening Sunne, Ile bee the Earth,</l>
               <l>And offer vp to Thee this gratefull birth</l>
               <l>Of thankes: which thus now giv'n, though ſtraight it Die,</l>
               <l>Jt has liv'd Ages in its Infancie.</l>
               <l>Action, not Time, does number age. Who giues</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20884:35"/>A iuſt praiſe to great Vertues Patrone, liues</l>
               <l>Himſelfe by his iuſt Gratitude. Let Spight</l>
               <l>Then doe its worſt, and with eternall night</l>
               <l>Labour to clowd my name. Obſcure to lie</l>
               <l>With Vertue, is an immortalitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THis laſh has but <hi>Sixe</hi> knots: but ſee thou mend;</l>
               <l>Or <hi>peradventure</hi> Elſe I ſhall intend.</l>
               <l>(Although my Angry <hi>Muſe</hi> ſaies Shee will bee</l>
               <l>No more thus Wit-bound, thus Tongue-tied, not Shee)</l>
               <l>To come in Fury; and thee Naked ſtrippe;</l>
               <l>And Scourge thee with a <hi>Sixteene</hi>-knotted whippe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
